<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony for God's everlasting truth as it hath been learned of and in Jesus testifying against such as through unbelief have departed from, or been disobedient to the spirit that conuinces the world of sin : among whom R.C. hath appeared with his many things, to oppose and withstand the one thing, the spirit of life, that sets free from sin and death, which is the truth which the people call Quakers have and do testifie to and of / R.T.</title>
            <author>R. T. (Rebecca Travers), 1609-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31972</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12283850</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12283850</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58809</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63079)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58809)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1515:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony for God's everlasting truth as it hath been learned of and in Jesus testifying against such as through unbelief have departed from, or been disobedient to the spirit that conuinces the world of sin : among whom R.C. hath appeared with his many things, to oppose and withstand the one thing, the spirit of life, that sets free from sin and death, which is the truth which the people call Quakers have and do testifie to and of / R.T.</title>
                  <author>R. T. (Rebecca Travers), 1609-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints to Travers.</note>
                  <note>Pages 44-45 misprinted 43-44.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 47.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:58809:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:58809:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A TESTIMONY for God's Everlaſting Truth, As it hath been learned of and in JESUS;</p>
            <p>Teſtifying againſt ſuch as through unbelief have departed from, or been diſobedient to the Spirit that convinces the World of Sin:</p>
            <p>Among whom <hi>R. C.</hi> hath appeared with his many things, to oppoſe and withſtand the one thing, the Spirit of Life, that ſets free from Sin and Death, which is the Truth which the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called <hi>Quakers</hi> have and do teſtifie to and of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us; but they went out, that they might be made manifeſt, that they were not of us,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But ye have an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction from the holy One, and ye know all things,</hi> V. 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This then is the meſſage which we have heard of him, and declare unto you, that God is Light, and in him is no Darkneſs at all,</hi> 1 Joh. 1. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beloved, when I gave all diligence to write unto you of the common Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, it was needfull for me to write unto you, and exhort you, that ye ſhould earneſtly contend for the faith which was once delivered to the Saints,</hi> Jude ver. 3.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1669.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:58809:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58809:2"/>
THeſe following Lines are to ſuch as have, or may meet with <hi>R. C's</hi> Writing, Entituled, <hi>God's Truth atteſted according to Scripture;</hi> and I reading it over, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it not only contrary to Scripture, but in darkneſs oppoſing and contradicting the Light and Spirit that gave forth the Scriptures; exalted and exalting his own image over and againſt the expreſs Image of the Everlaſting God, I could not but in anſwer thereto give unto you what I have received of the Fountain of Life; which all that make oppoſition againſt the Light and Spirit which is Everlaſting, are out from, and know neither the Soul that God takes pleaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, nor the Salvation thereof, but remains in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and under the power of Death, not knowing the Gift of God which is Eternal Life; but to ſo many as believe in him <hi>[the Light of the World]</hi> he giveth power to be the Sons of God, Heirs with him, yea Co-heirs of the Inheritance of Light and Glory.</p>
            <p>So to all mankind, I and all that partake of the common ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation (that hath appeared unto all, for deliverance from death, and Deaths power, again to recover into the good ſtate that was before tranſgreſsion entred, or the Night of Apoſtacy over ſpread the Earth; for Light was in the beginning, and indeed the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of all, and ſhall abide when all imaginations ſhall ceaſe;) and by Faith therein have obtained Life, have good will unto every one, travelling therein to bring others thereto, and to preſerve out of the many ſnares which the evil One hath and doth lay to deceive; but the increaſe of Light, and the dominion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of muſt never have end, and the enlargment and growth hereof hath and doth inrage the whole World that love Darkneſs better then Light; ſo they have bent their Bowes, and prepared their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and their tongues are become as a two-edged Sword, to wound the Innocent, for the poyſon of Aſps is under that which ſpeaks di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitefully againſt the Spirit of Grace; for no other have the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Light teſtified of, or believed in, but the Spirit of Jeſus, which they that do and have erred from are deviſing againſt,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58809:3"/>
and ſo cry up the greatneſs of their own <hi>Diana,</hi> to turn aſide or draw out of the way of peace; but he has, &amp; will rebuke them, yea in his hot diſpleaſure, who either rage or imagine vain things againſt his Chriſt, which he will exalt above all the Mountains: and ſuch is my love, and the love of all that in the love of the Father live, that we deſire none might periſh, but have Life Everlaſting, which the Father giveth freely unto all, without reſpect of perſons, that in his Light believe and walk, to receive Salvation thereby; and ſo this is teſtified of, and ſpoke to in all, that all that come to the Faith of it, may with us witneſs it ſaves from ſin; and his Name was and is called <hi>Jeſus,</hi> but all out of the Faith diſcern it not; how ſhould they, being carnally minded? though it ſomtimes prick them, they kick againſt it, and to pervert from it lay ſtumblings in the way, and bring forth their carnal imagination of God and Chriſt, and of his Perſon and Fleſh, which was never learned, but in that they reſiſt; for darkneſs cannot comprehend Light, but in the Light is Life and Salvation; and this they have, and do bear teſtimony of, who have learned the Truth, as it is in Chriſt Jeſus; and for the Truth ſake which muſt prevail over all the Oppoſers thereof, and for your Souls ſake this is written, that no ſimple ones may be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the way, nor ſtumble or fall, but come to believe in the Light, and the redemption thereof they will come to be partakers of, and there is no other that can work the work of God, to free from evil and error, but the Chriſt of God, the expreſs Image of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, only learned in the Spirit and Light that cometh or proceeds from the Father &amp; Son, and the obedient and faithful thereto have been, and are led out of the World where Sin and Error are, to the victory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver it, and ſuch will not believe only from what we declare of it, though it be true, but finding this heavenly Treaſure in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the freedom thereby attained, ſhall confeſs this is the Son of God that maketh free indeed; and I know they who are not captivated under the power of Sin and Darkneſs, nor lovers of themſelves more then of God, will feel that in the Love of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Souls of all this is written.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58809:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> TESTIMONY <hi>for God's Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting</hi> TRUTH, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Light which I with many thouſands have believed in, and found, ſaves from ſin, and none in the Faith of God, are at a queſtion what it is, but know it is of the Father, bringing to the Life, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> whoſe firſt appearance was and ever is to <hi>condemn ſin</hi> in the <hi>fleſh;</hi> and being believed in, quickneth in Spirit, by which only the Son of God was &amp; is revealed; and all that have gone another way to know the Father or the Son, but in the Spirit of Jeſus, are vain Image-makers, Robbers, and Theeves, leaving the Door, to clime another way; So <hi>none cometh unto me but whom the Father draws,</hi> and by the Spirit only is the drawing, ſaith <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which is Life and Salvation, witneſſed by all that have Faith therein, and this is that which, according to his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs that hath promiſed, is and muſt be exalted over all, that in darkneſs have and do invent againſt the Light; amongſt which R. C. will be found a worker, to whom I have this to ſay, that if they were and are accurſed that come not forth to help the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the mighty; What ſhall become of thee, and ſuch as have helped the mighty in force and falſhood againſt the Lord? who will bring to paſs (as he hath ſpoken) Light and Salvation to the ends of the Earth; and all that contend againſt it ſhall fall before it, and thou as one ſtrong to deceive; and therefore wouldſt colour thy work with that which teſtifies againſt thee; Saying, in thy title, <hi>thou wilt atteſt according to Scripture,</hi> and ſo beginſt with a lye, for thou deteſts both Scripture and the words of Chriſt therein; for thou denieſt his Doctrine, and calleſt it a new opinion to preach the Light up <hi>for Chriſt;</hi> though Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the Light of the World;</hi> how hath Satan deceived thee, that thou ſhouldeſt think any ſhould receive thy <hi>fallaſies,</hi> that callſt the Doctrine which Chriſt &amp; the Apoſtles taught <hi>fallaſies?</hi> ſhalt thou or the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved?
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58809:4"/>
he ſaith, <hi>In the beginnining was the Word, and the Word was God, and by him</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">But he in his Queries denies Chriſt to make all things; ſo we marvel not that he ſhould deny our Doctrine, that denies Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</note> 
               <hi>all things were made, and in him was Life, and the Life were the Light of men, and this is the true Light that enlighteneth every man,</hi> and thou lightly and ſlightly ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; <hi>this of the firſt of</hi> John <hi>is their ground,</hi> and ſo reſiſts the Scripture, and yet ſaith thou wilt atteſt according to Scripture, and then ſpeaks of the <hi>Humanity in conjunction with the Deity;</hi> ſo far art thou from atteſting according to Scripture, that the words thou uſeſt I never read in Scripture, but know, they with other words uſed by thee, have not a ground from the Scriptures, (as thou confeſſeſt the Preachers of the Light have) but from the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Spirit, that having deſpiſed the Light, and offered deſpight unto the Spirit of Grace, cannot expreſs their matters and inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Language of the Spirit, by which the Scriptures were given forth, except they ſteal them where they are already written; and ſo have joyned words in the dark, where all images are framed; and amongſt theſe thou haſt got ſom to ſtrengthen thee againſt the Light, and to lay falſehood on the obeyers thereof, in ſaying, <hi>they deny the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Humanity of our Lord;</hi> who is thy lord, indeed is to be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but <hi>the Lord from Heaven by whom all things were made,</hi> thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heardſt any to deny, that have faith in the Light; or any of thoſe names which the Scripture gives, as <hi>the man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> as <hi>he that became fleſh</hi> and <hi>lived amongſt us;</hi> and that was, and is a great Myſtery, <hi>God manifeſted in fleſh, the Chriſt indeed,</hi> appointed of God, to be both Prieſt and King; and for thy atteſting according to Scripture, is only a relating what thou haſt read; which Pope and Prelate as well as thee can talk of the Virgins conceiving, bringing forth, and of Chriſts Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, Death, &amp; Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, &amp; none of thoſe things there written didſt thou ever hear denied by any of the Children of Light: But the imaginations of others, and thee thereon, were and are to be teſtified againſt; for it was vain imaginations that the Lord did and doth complain on; and however thou cameſt to be in Priſon, and elſewhere with the people of the Lord; yet it was then ſeen and in that which diſcerns, that the chamber of imagery was never deſtroyed in thee, nor the old bottle broken, but the ground ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in thee that brings forth Briers and Thorns, and is neer unto cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58809:4"/>
and the fruits thereof thou haſt brought forth, in perverting ſome, and laying ſtumblings in the way of the ſimple; thou wert a climer at the firſt, and got ſome words of the fame of Life, but was and art in Death, and to this day bringeſt forth therein; and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in blindneſs thy ſelf, thinkeſt others cannot ſee; and ſo after thy relating part of what is written, concerning Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>we ſee,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou, <hi>what Teſtimony the Scriptures gives of the Lord's Chriſt, that he is not the Light in any mans Conſcience, nor the Principle of Light:</hi> art thou not aſhamed to call to ſee that which cannot be ſeen? for doth the Scriptures any where ſay Chriſt is not the Light in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, nor the Principle of Light? ſo, ſee thy work is to deceive, and make people believe lies; whoſe work art thou a doing, that art drawing from believing in the Light, to believe a lye? doth not the Scriptures by the mouth of Chriſt ſay, believe in the Light? and do the Scriptures hold out any Faith, or any to believe in, but Chriſt? and is not the cauſe and being of all things Chriſt? and yet thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieſt him to be the principle of Light; what would thy dark minde make the principle of Light, that denies the Lord Chriſt, that ſaith, <hi>I am the Light of the World?</hi> thou ſheweſt thy ignorance of the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Faith which in the pure Conſcience is hid; but whoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is defiled, and feared, hath no feeling of Light nor Faith, and ſo would blind the eyes of others, to lead captive as the Divil doth all that diſobey the Light; for it is an everlaſting Truth, <hi>who reſiſt the Light, that gave forth the Scriptures, doth pervert the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to their own deſtruction,</hi> not knowing the Interpreter of a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, for in the motion of Light and Spirit were the Scriptures given forth, and by the ſame only is the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Holy men gave them forth as they were moved of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 21.</note> true underſtanding thereof, and thoſe that have, and do bring forth, without being learned of the Light, have filled the World with Errors and Falſhoods; <hi>Babel</hi> indeed, and thou a chief Builder therein, ignorant <hi>of the Covenant of Light, Chriſt the Covenant to Gods people,</hi> and a <hi>Light unto the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles to the ends of the Earth;</hi> thus ſaith <note place="margin">
                  <hi>As the Prophet</hi> Iſaiah <hi>and old</hi> Simeon <hi>declared.</hi>
               </note> the Scripture, with much more in Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to and for the Truth, he is the Light of the World; and ſo all that have an eye to ſee may ſee, that thou
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58809:5"/>
goeſt about to atteſt a Lye, and the Scriptures teſtifie againſt thee, and are contrary to thy Doctrine, that denyeſt the Chriſt of God; who art framing an Image; but thy Snare is broken, and all that love and obey the Light, have and ſhall eſcape, and thy own work ſhall turn upon thee; <hi>for he that commanded Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, hath ſhined into our hearts, to give us the knowledg of himſelf, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> but who reſiſts the ſhining in their own hearts, wax worſe and worſe until they come to war againſt that, to which thoſe ſent of God turned men to, <hi>from Darkneſs to Light, from the Power of Satan unto the Power of God;</hi> but who ſent thee, that turns from the Power of Light, to believe thy dark Imaginations, of a <hi>creaturely Soul?</hi> and inſtead of bringing Scripture for thy Proof, thou bringeſt a Proof from <hi>Beamond,</hi> or thy own Imaginations, that <hi>we ſhould have found our ſouls creaturely from the flames of the Righteous burnings of Gods Wrath in our ſouls for ſin;</hi> Oh, thick Darkneſs! is this thy Argument to prove the Soul creaturely, that it can live with everlaſting burnings; the leaſt child of Light could give thee a clearer knowledg of the Soul, then thee, or thy Teacher J. B. ever attained to; but who hates the Light is, and muſt be bound in Chains of Darkneſs for evermore, and there I leave thee, in that matter as concerning the Soul, and return to thy opinion of the Light: thou ſayeſt in thy fourth page, <hi>Chriſt is not the Principle of Light,</hi> and in the ſixth page thou ſayeſt, <hi>the Light in the Conſcience which theſe new Preachers cry up for Chriſt, is but the Principle of Chriſt, which is his own Habitation:</hi> This is ſuch Logick as the Framers of <hi>Babel</hi> uſe to Build with; vain Phyloſophy indeed, from which all that believe in the Light know redemption; how different is thy Way and Doctrine from the Way of the Lord, where the wafering man, though a fool, errs not; wherein the ſimple may walk &amp; be ſafe; but what profit is there of thy winding and turning Chriſt not the principle of Light, yet Light the principle of Chriſt? what ſerves thy opinion and Doctrine for? but to lay ſtumblings in the way of the ſimple, and inſtead of appearing wiſer then others, thou haſt bewrayed thy ignorance in this thy work, and former practiſes, in perverting from the good Way of the Lord, not knowing what thou ſayeſt nor whereof thou affirmeſt; haſt thou not yet learned what the word <hi>Principle</hi> is? is it not the <hi>beginning?</hi> is not Chriſt the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58809:5"/>
of all things? <note n="‖" place="margin">Thou in thy Queries ſayeſt, all was not made by Chriſt, contrary to Light or to Scripture.</note> by him, and for him was all made; and yet wilt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him to be the beginning, or Principle of Light, as in thy fourth page, and in thy ſixth page thou ſayeſt, Light is but the Principle of Chriſt, ſo whilſt in thy Dark minde, thou wouldſt debaſe the Light in the conſcience, ſee how thou haſt lifted it up; for inſtead of ſaying the Light comes from Chriſt, thou holdeſt out the Light to be the beginning of Chriſt; for doth not every rational Creature know the principle of any thing is before that which comes of it? <hi>the Principle of Chriſt</hi> ſayeſt thou? <hi>which is his own Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> ſo thou confeſſeſt the Light in the Conſcience to be the dwelling place of God, and yet would cry out againſt ſuch as preach the Light in the conſcience; thou doſt indeed darken knowledg by words without underſtanding; for never any that deſpiſed the Light knew him that is the Light of the World, or his Dwelling place: thou haſt deviſed againſt that which is too hard for thee; may all the Enemies of the Light be covered with confuſion, as thou art; then thou goeſt on (in the ſame page 6.) again to make a relation of his Death, Reſurection and Aſcenſion, and ſo ſaying no more, nor ſo much in that matter then formerly I have taught a Child or Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of 7 years old to ſay; and here ſayeſt thou, <hi>that Opinion is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the Scriptures that denies the Aſcenſion of the Lords Perſon;</hi> who they be that deny the aſcenſion of the Lords Chriſt I know not; for all that have Faith in the Light bare teſtimony thereto; but for the word perſon, is it any where written in Scripture his Perſon Aſcended? how dareſt thou add to the words? and thou farther ſayeſt, that <hi>our Foundation is built upon the ground of Nature:</hi> if thou hadſt ſaid our Foundation is the ground, or cauſe, or being of all natural things, thou hadſt ſpoke true, though thou knoweſt it not, for by him that is our Foundation <hi>all things were made<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>without it was nothing made that was made,</hi> John 1. 2. <hi>and this is the true Light that enlightens every man that comes into the World;</hi> and the Children of Light never denied his Perſon, that took upon him the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> became fleſh, and lived amongſt us: ſo inſtead of proving the Children of Light in error, thou haſt proved thy ſelf an Accuſer, and the Scripture hath and doth teſtifie againſt thee, for us, that have not, nor do not declare of any other Chriſt, but he of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58809:6"/>
whom the Scriptures declare to be the Light of the World: and ſo thou goeſt on to repeat many good words in the relation of ſome thing written in the Scriptures, and adds thy own words, that <hi>the everlaſting Goſpel is his Death, Burial and Reſurrection, as the Scriptures declare,</hi> (ſayeſt thou) and notes a Scripture to prove it, that is not to be found in all the Bible 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 25. 1. is this to atteſt by Scripture to direct to that which was never there? but the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>the Goſpel is the Power of God unto Salvation,</hi> and that the <hi>Word in the heart, and in the mouth,</hi> was the Goſpel he preached, and the everlaſting Goſpel proclaimed by an Angel through Heaven was, <hi>fear God and give Glory to him, for the hour of his Righteous Judgments is come;</hi> theſe did not ſay Chriſt's Death and Burial were the Goſpel, but who are Witneſſes of his Reſurrection do know the Goſpel; but the Oppoſers of the Light in Conſcience ſee it not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But to take farther notice of thy unlearned words, the reſt of thy 7th page is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſuch words as thou haſt either borrow'd or rather ſtolen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou nameſt not the Author, from <hi>Beamon,</hi> or it may be ſome of <hi>John Jackſons,</hi> for he once brought out ſuch a work of Darkneſs as thine is, and thou haſt the ſame words, ſo the anſwer given him may come over this part of thy work; for Truth muſt forever be over the head of Falſhood: and thou that ſayeſt thou wouldſt <hi>atteſt thy truth according to Scripture,</hi> thou draweſt a concluſion from thy own, and thy borrowed words, without any Scripture; and now, ſayeſt thou, that <hi>it is manifeſt from hence that this Light that doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the Heathen's, is not the Lord Chriſt that doth juſtifie;</hi> but ſhews neither good reaſon nor Scripture for it; but makes mention of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> which words being taken as they were given forth by the Apoſtle proves thy affirmation falſe, for the Apoſtles words are theſe, ſpeaking to the <hi>Romans</hi> or <hi>Heathens,</hi> Rom. 1. 19. <hi>The wrath of God is revealed from Heaven againſt all ungodlineſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs of men, who hold the Truth in unrighteouſneſs, becauſe that which may be known of God is manifeſt in them; for God hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it unto them:</hi> now without <hi>R. C.</hi> can make any ſo blind as himſelf, will <hi>Pauls</hi> words here, or any where, prove that he which Condemns is not Chriſt that Juſtifies? and farther, would not theſe words prove againſt thee that brings the proof that the Truth is held in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs by the <hi>Heathens?</hi> for is not Chriſt the Truth? but who knows not Chriſt to be the Light, knows him not to be the Truth,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58809:6"/>
and ſo builds on a lye, and makes lyes the defence thereof; but who have faith in the Light, by which the Scriptures were given forth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them, and to them they witneſs, that into Chriſt's Hands all Judgment is given, and he was made manifeſt <hi>to deſtroy the works of the Devil;</hi> doth not he Condemn that which he Deſtroys? and haſt thou not read that his firſt Appearance was and is to Condemn ſin in the fleſh? thus ſay the Scriptures; but thou ſayeſt <hi>he is not the Juſtifier that condemns;</hi> ſo the Scriptures ſay, Chriſt condemns, and whom he juſtifies none can condemn; but thou wouldſt have another to juſtifie then the Chriſt of God, into whoſe hands God hath committed all Judgment; but, ſayeſt thou, the <hi>Romans had this Light, though they were Heathens;</hi> yea, they had, and didſt thou know and believe the Scriptures, wouldſt thou thus write, and ſay, thou wouldſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt by Scripture, and write contrary to it? Is not the Promiſe and Covenant of the Father, Chriſt? and did not Prophets and Apoſtles teſtifie of him? and ſay not the Scriptures, <hi>I will give him for a Covenant to my People, and a Light unto the Gentiles?</hi> the ſame that was the Covenant to them that believe the ſame, was a Light to the <hi>Heathens,</hi> as ſay the Prophets; not two, but one: and as ſaith Chriſt, <hi>The Comforter ſhall come, and this ſhall condemn the World of ſin:</hi> And ſo, is it not plain that he that condemns the Sinner com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts the Saints? and that is the Juſtifier; him that Chriſt ſaith <hi>ſhould convince and reprove the World of Sin, of Righteouſneſs, and of Judgment,</hi> was and is Comforter and Juſtifier, <hi>For we are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in Spirit,</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle, and by this only come to know the Father and Son in the Spirit and Light, and deſire no more to know him after the Fleſh, as ſaith the Apoſtle; but thou bringeſt a Doctrine contrary to Chriſt, Prophets, and Apoſtles<hi>:</hi> for, ſayeſt thou, <hi>the Apoſtles came not to turn them to that Light that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes or excuſes them, as their Saviour; but preached Chriſt Jeſus at Jeruſalem:</hi> be aſhamed to affirm falſhood; did not the Apoſtle ſay, <hi>he was ſent to turn from Darkneſs to Light<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi> and did they ever preach two Lights, as thou wouldſt do? but gave all to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that that which did accuſe was that which did excuſe, <hi>and that the Grace which brought Salvation had appeared unto all men, and taught them that believed therein, to deny all ungodlineſs,</hi> and to this <hi>he committed all, to the Word of Grace, that was able to ſave their Souls;</hi> telling them, he was an able Miniſter of the Spirit, and not of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58809:7"/>
Letter; and did not run over the Hiſtory of Chriſt's Conception, Birth, Death and Reſurrection in words, as thou doſt, but turned them to that Light and Spirit whereby they had learned him; though his outward appearance at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> he never ſaw, nor deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any more to know after the Fleſh; but preſſed all to obedience of that Grace and Light that he had found the ſufficiency of; decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Son of God was revealed in him; and <hi>his travel was, that Chriſt might be formed in them,</hi> to whom he was ſent preaching to them, <hi>That a meaſure of the Spirit was given to every one to profit withal:</hi> ſo let all that have an eye ſee whether the Scriptures of Truth give teſtimony to thy Doctrine, that would prove them in Error that cry up the Light for Salvation; or thy Doctrine, that ſays, <hi>Chriſt is not the Light in every mans Conſcience, nor yet the Principle of Light;</hi> the wiſe in heart can judge: And then goeſt on, and ſayeſt, <hi>The Light in the Conſcience is but the Law:</hi> it is the <hi>Law</hi> indeed, that if thou hadſt not thrown behind thy back, thou mightſt have come to have known the new Covenant <hi>[Chriſt]</hi> which God promiſed in the laſt dayes <hi>to write in the heart;</hi> and this did and doth make perfect, teaching, and bringing, or binding to God, that they ſhall not depart from him: and he that abideth with him, not departing from him, is perfect in him, and by him in the <hi>Law of the Spirit of Grace, that ſets free from Sin and Death.</hi> But of this Law thou art not learned, nor of him that was made under the Law, that art uſing the Apoſtles words ſpoken of the Law in the Letter, to oppoſe the Law of the Spirit<hi>:</hi> but who are come to the Law of the Spirit, know freedom, and that he is Chriſt that ſets free; and ſuch thou ſhalt never turn backward, who by believing in the Light have found Salvation, and know, <hi>that he which ſaves is Jeſus,</hi> and by his Power hath freedom in Righteouſneſs from all that has or would oppreſs the holy Seed: and this is the Son that hath ſet free, even the Chriſt of God. And thy tongue confeſſes, that the Believers in the Light, and they only have attained freedom in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and cannot be entangled with the cunning deceits of men. And for theſe thy following words (page 8.) now that Chriſt is <hi>Light, who is he that denies; but that Chriſt is the Light of Conſcience, who is he that will not deny,</hi> (ſayeſt thou.) Indeed R. thou doſt in this manifeſt what thou art a battering &amp; breaking, thy own works, for Truth is out of thy reach: for didſt thou ever all thy time thou
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58809:7"/>
wert in Priſon, or elſewhere with us, ever hear any preach up, (or write) the Light of Conſcience? It ſeems thou are both deaf and blind, and ſo art to remain till by obedience to the Light (thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents againſt) thou comeſt to be for the Light that we believe, teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie of, and call to, is Everlaſting, and none in thy comprehending nature knows the power and glory thereof: and ſo ſuch as thou haſt thou bringſt forth; and having a Lump of thy own framing, a <hi>formed light, created light,</hi> or <hi>light of a Conſcience</hi> that may be defiled, and ſets this up, wouldſt make people believe thy image were our God: and ſo falls a beating thy own image, crying, who will not deny. I anſwer, all who believe in that true Light deny all and every of thy imaginations, to be Chriſt; and from the knowledg of the true Chriſt, are all Image-makers ſhut out.</p>
            <p>Yet another Chriſt then he that dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> didſt thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hear the Children of Light declare, or teſtifie of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to, and he is not divided, he and his Light is one: and thou confeſſeſt he is a Light, and yet not in the Conſcience.</p>
            <p>But Darkneſs cannot comprehend Light; and as for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainer of thy eighth page, and the greateſt part of thy nineth page, being but a repetition of ſome of J. B's dark ſayings, or writings of that Hiſtory of Scripture, formerly being taken notice of; with ſome like Logick, as thou haſt before mentioned I ſhall paſs; but in the latter end of thy 9th page, thou thus concluds; <hi>now having this Demonſtration from Scripture of the aſcenſion of the body of our Lord Jeſus; and this</hi> (thou ſayeſt) <hi>may judg them that would have Chriſt all Spirit and no Body:</hi> To this I cannot but anſwer, who they are that deny Chriſt's Body or Aſcenſion, (as in Scripture it is declared) I know not; for all that confeſs to the Light in Conſcience teſtifie thereto; but thou mayſt well miſtake others Doctrine that ſo forgets thy own<hi>!</hi> as to ſay, now having this demonſtrated from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Aſcenſion of the Body of our Lord, when there is not a word brought by thee (in a page or two before) of Scripture to prove it; but that he Aſcended into Glory, and we in the Faith know it; but for thy ſo ſtoutly affirming by Scriptures, that thou haſt no Scripture for, it will appear unto all that have an eye to ſee but as Sorcery; even as <hi>Jannes and Jambres withſtood Moſes, ſo thou withſtands the Truth:</hi> and thoſe who through negligence to attend, or diſobedience to the Light have been overtaken with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58809:8"/>
the Night, have or may ſtumble at thy work of Darkneſs: yet who have learned of the Light, the Truth, as it is in Jeſus, thou canſt not turn aſide: For what manner of blind ſtuff doeſt thou bring forth, as though thou wouldſt make people believe thou haſt Scripture, againſt thoſe that confeſs to the Light in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but canſt bring none againſt them, and ſo brings for them; and confeſſes the <hi>birth of their opinion is from the firſt of</hi> John: ſo thou confeſſeſt they to whom thou oppoſeſt have Scripture to prove; but thou art ſo far from having any to prove thy words and imaginations, that thou wouldſt if thou knew'ſt how deny the Scripture, that thou mighteſt hide Light and Truth, by thy ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, thou ſets up a fiction, and accuſes us of it; for ſayeſt thou, <hi>where it is ſaid of Chriſt, not of Light of Conſcience:</hi> I would thou wert ſo honeſt as to ſpeak true words, and then thou wouldſt confeſs, that though for years thou haſt watched for evil againſt us, thou never heardſt any amongſt the Children of Light, but declare, what is ſpoken in the firſt of <hi>John</hi> was ſpoke of Chriſt, and that by his own Light and Spirit was he to be learned, as ſays the Scripture, <hi>A man ſent of God to bear Teſtimony to the Light;</hi> did he bear Teſtimony to an other then Chriſt? no, all that have been, or are ſent of him teſtifie of the Light; but they that run and are not ſent, ſtrive againſt it, as thou doeſt, and bring the Scripture that ſayes, the <hi>Life of Chriſt is the Light of men, and be it is that inlightneth every man that comes into the World; and that the Scriptures are true, none contends with us about that; but that we underſtand not our own Doctrine, and thence ſet up a fiction of our own invention:</hi> doeſt thou think thy denying to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with us about the Scriptures, when all that can ſee do ſee thou doeſt contend, will make any believe thy accuſation that we do not underſtand our own Doctrine, and ſo ſet up a fiction? why haſt not thou with thy great underſtanding, that ſeems ſo wiſe in thy own eyes, as to gainſay the Truth that is received and believed by thouſands, come forth, and tell where this Light teſtified of by the Apoſtle is, if not in the Conſcience? for thy fancy is contrary to the Apoſtle, <hi>that appealed to that of God in every mans Conſcience, and to that was manifeſt:</hi> but where the conſcience is ſeared, they ſee not, nor feel not, and being out of the Truth, which is now where to be found, but where God requires it, in <hi>the inner parts;</hi> and who are gone out to ſeek it abroad, whatever they may think of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58809:8"/>
their own Doctrines, know nothing of the Truth; but are found contenders againſt it, and againſt the Scriptures; which teſtifie of him that is the Chriſt of God, <hi>to be in the Heart and in the Mouth; that he dwels in Light;</hi> and thou haſt confeſſed in thy words, though in darkneſs, not knowing what thou ſayeſt: <hi>that in Conſcience is Gods Habitation;</hi> yet art contending that any ſhould preach Chriſt the Light in the Conſcience; is he not in his dwelling place,? does not the Scripture ſay, <hi>God dwels in Light, and that God is in Chriſt,</hi> and that <hi>he will gather all things unto him?</hi> and <hi>is not Chriſt the Reſt, into which all that the Father hath given him muſt be gathered into him and be in him?</hi> as ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I in them, and thou in me:</hi> So thou haſt proved Chriſt the Light in the Conſcience, when thou goeſt about to diſprove it, confeſſing the Light in the Conſcience the Principle of Chriſt, and his own Habitation, and they his whom the Father gives him: and Chriſt ſaid, I in them, ſo the Scriptures prove, that according to Scripture thou atteſt not, but contrary thereto, that ſayeſt, <hi>God hath made a formed Light for a Habitation of mans Reſt,</hi> Page 7. What new opinion art thou a crying up, that art ſetting up another reſt for Gods people then Chriſt? what wouldſt thou have them reſt in? <hi>a formed Light (ſayeſt thou)</hi> God is Light ſaith the Scripture, but no where that he was formed that gave form and being to all: and another Light then that which gives Salvation did not the people of God ever ſeek, or find to be a Reſt, but he that ſaves from ſin, and <hi>his Name is Jeſus,</hi> and in him thouſands are come to know ſure Salvation by the Light made manifeſt in Conſcience, and are kept thereby, that they could no more believe thy <hi>formed light,</hi> nor Doctrine thereof, then in the Papiſts Euchariſt, which indeed are both Idols, formed in one ground, and the Scripture plentifully teſtifies againſt you both; yet the Papiſt in their carnal underſtanding have a Scripture for their Idols; but where canſt thou get any word to make a cover for thy Image; that ſayeſt, <hi>I give you to know, that the Light in Conſcience is but the ſpirit of the humane Soul, and is creaturely?</hi> what Scripture haſt thou for the ground of thy Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? So all that love the Light ſee thy ground is not from Scripture; there not being a word from the firſt of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> to the laſt of the <hi>Revelation</hi> for this thy new Doctrines, for a <hi>formed light, made into a habitation for mans Reſt, and the Light of the Conſcience, but the</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58809:9"/>
               <hi>ſpirit of the humane nature:</hi> And ſo thou that in thy Title ſayeſt, <hi>thou wouldſt atteſt by Scripture,</hi> art teaching new Doctrine, that thou haſt no word in the Scripture for.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, in page 10. thou ſayeſt, our Doctrine is this, <hi>That which makes manifeſt is Light, and the Light is Chriſt:</hi> and haſt not thou in theſe words manifeſted thy ſelf to be a Contender againſt Scripture, as well as againſt us that in the Spirit that gave forth the Scripture witneſs; and therefore to us doth it witneſs: for are not thoſe very words (as thou ſayeſt we ſay) the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>that it is Light that manifeſts?</hi> ſo ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I am the Light:</hi> ſo thou contends with the People of the Lord, for ſaying as the Apoſtle and Chriſt ſays. Then thou goeſt on to ask three Queſtions: Firſt, <hi>Was the Light in mans Conſcience that perſonal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance that</hi> John <hi>bore witneſs to.</hi> (Second, <hi>Was the Light in mans Conſcience that word of God that was God, by which all things were made that were made.)</hi> Third, <hi>Was the Light in Conſcience perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to be ſeen by the firmental eye, to be felt with the outward hand.</hi> And from theſe thy own words, thou draweſt a concluſion, <hi>that if the Light of Conſcience be not to be underſtood in theſe capcities, our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is falſe:</hi> Though thou haſt brought no more reaſon to prove it. then if thou hadſt ſaid, <hi>I would have it ſo;</hi> for as to the Apoſtles words we teſtifie, and have learned in that Spirit, which the carnal man could never diſcern, nor the things thereof; but the Apoſtle anſwers himſelf, and hath declared, of whom he teſtified, by whom all things were made; <hi>and that this was the true Light, that enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth every man that cometh into the World;</hi> and it was the Chriſt of God which he bore Teſtimony to; ſo inſtead of proving us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> error that confeſs Chriſt the Light in every Conſcience, thou bringſt thy ſelf under the Plagues threatned for adding to the Scriptures<hi>:</hi> For where did ever the Apoſtle, in that place, or any other, ſpeak of <hi>perſonal and firmental,</hi> as thou doſt, and conclude all falſe that are not of thy mind? And to anſwer thee further, the Apoſtle did preach and teſtifie of Chriſt, and as he taught him, ſo is he learned in Light or Spirit; is not this in the Conſcience? How wouldſt thou have <hi>Chriſt ſeen, felt and handled? how is Chriſt with his people to the end of the World,</hi> according to his Promiſe? and <hi>how is he in them that was with them?</hi> Is it to be ſeen <hi>firmental,</hi> as thou calleſt? though no other did the Apoſtle teſtifie of, then he that became fleſh, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58809:9"/>
dwelt amongſt us: yet <hi>no more did they know him after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit:</hi> but thou, and ſuch as thou, who in your carnal minds would comprehend ſpiritual things, bring forth your carnal apprehenſions, and having no knowledg but what you have ſenſually, know neither Chriſt's Fleſh nor glorious Body, but that which could be pierced, wounded and crucified, all Image-makers are ſtill oppreſſing; for he is ſtill ſlayn in ſpiritual <hi>Egypt</hi> where thou art: and though thou knoweſt, we, that thou ſeemeſt to ſtrike at, did and do confeſs to him, and no other, that made a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion before <hi>Pilate,</hi> of whom <hi>John</hi> bear witneſs to be <hi>the Light of the World;</hi> and this is true, and they are found Liars before God, that would ſet up any thing to be believed in, but he that in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is revealed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for thouſands of thoſe that ſaw his perſonal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> knew him not to be the Chriſt; nay, by Spirit then was he to be learned, as thou may read, where <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſeth him; and Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Fleſh and Blood hath not revealed this to thee, but the Spirit of my Father,</hi> and againſt this art thou fighting, and thoſe that are lead thereby, for by Light and Spirit have we learned Chriſt, and ſo teach him; and this is he which is teſtified of, that is the Eternal Gift of God, and he that is ſent of God, <hi>whom to know is Eternal Life;</hi> but of this are they all ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that call the Light in Conſcience <hi>a formed thing, and the Spirit of the humane earthly Soul,</hi> but their ignorance of the great Power of God is not to be marvelled at, that ſays, <hi>The Light and Spirit is of the humane earthly ſoul;</hi> and ſo would make all believe, that the ſouls of men and women were no other then the Dogs, or Cats, and Beaſts that muſt periſh, for what is of the Farth muſt to the Earth: haſt thou not read, <hi>God breathed into man, and he became a living Soul?</hi> and thou calleſt this <hi>Human or Earthly;</hi> needs then muſt they ſtumble and fall, that walk in the dark, as thou<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and all do that would comprehend the Light to diſpute again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; but over thee, and all vain Image-makers it ſhall riſe, that with your dark Images and inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have filled the World with Idolatry, Profainneſs and Athiſm; and what doctrine more then thine doth it? that preacheſt the Soul <hi>Human and Creaturely and the Light formed of it;</hi> ſo neither Soul nor Light Immortal &amp; Eternal, but of the Earth; a beaſtly doctrine, which hath manifeſted the Teacher to know nothing but what he knows ſenſually: yet thou goeſt on repeating what Chriſt did and ſuffered,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58809:10"/>
when manifeſt at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and then ſayeſt, <hi>this manifeſts Chriſt is Formative, and not a Defuſive Principle;</hi> this, like thy former ſtuff, which thou haſt got in thy dark mind, &amp; ſo in dark words expreſſeſt it; what manner of Chriſt thou wouldſt have people believe in, all in the Light ſee; but the Chriſt of God is he that filleth all things, as the Scriptures teſtifie<hi>:</hi> And then thou goeſt on to confeſs, <hi>that the Light of conſcience was in the Apoſtles, and by this</hi> Peter <hi>confeſſed Chriſt to be the Son of God:</hi> How hath Satan blinded thee, that loves darkneſs better then Light! that thou ſhouldſt bring this Scripture, that calleſt the Light <hi>the Spirit of the human Soul;</hi> and Chriſt ſaith <hi>the Spirit of the Father revealed it in</hi> Peter: and was not, and is not Chriſt in the Father? ſo whatever thou haſt denied, thou haſt now proved Father, Spirit and Son the Light in the Conſcience; for they were never divided: or elſe thou muſt hold after thy former dark doctrine, the Father and the Spirit are <hi>but the Spirit of the human Soul:</hi> thus ſhall all they be ſnared that invent againſt the Truth, which is the ſame yeſterday to day and for ever; and let them all be ſo confounded, as thou art, that deviſe againſt the Light, ſaith my ſoul; for thou ſayeſt, <hi>Peter by his Light in Conſcience bares witneſs to Chriſt the Son of God;</hi> and Chriſt ſaith, not <hi>Fleſh and blood, but the Spirit of my Father revealed it;</hi> and knoweſt thou not that God is one, not divided? <hi>I in the Father, and the Father in me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt; and <hi>none aſcends to Heaven, but he that comes down from Heaven, the Son of man in Heaven;</hi> but this thou, nor any that ſaith <hi>the Light is the ſpirit of the humane ſoul,</hi> could ever ſee; but who in the Light and Spirit learn him, know he filleth all things, even the ſame to whom <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſed bleſt for ever; as ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>One God and Father of all, who is above all, and thorow all, and in you all,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 6. and this is he we teſtifie of, that dwells in the Light in Conſcience, where thou confeſſeſt the Son of God is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed; and yet ſayeſt the Light in Conſcience is not Chriſt; for he ſaith, he <hi>is aſcended far above all Heavens, that he may fill all things;</hi> and then goeſt on, ſaying, <hi>Now, O man, open thy eyes, and ſee how dangerouſly thou ſtandeſt, that denies the Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in his Perſon.</hi> And to this I anſwer, none that diſcerns it can or doth deny it, and <hi>their eyes</hi> are open to ſee thy confuſion, that wouldſt prove that the Light in Conſcience is not Chriſt, by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this proof that he aſcended that he might fill all things; O groſs
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58809:10"/>
darkneſs<hi>!</hi> Doth he fill all things, yet not the Conſcience? or haſt thou ſo long ſtrove againſt the Light in Conſcience, that thou ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteſt Conſcience nothing? for if any thing, then thou proveſt he is in it; for he fills all things: and doth he fill with darkneſs, or with Light? for thy following words in the latter end of thy 11th page, are a falſe Accuſation, in ſaying, <hi>We make that Body that did the Fathers Will, by whom we are ſaved, to be extinguiſhed, and as to any Subſtance vaniſhed away as ſmoke.</hi> To this I anſwer, I never knew any that had faith in the Light (againſt which thou haſt been deviſing) deny Chriſt's Body, but all ſuch know it is a glorious Body: and ſo there needs not much be ſaid to a Lye, but the Truth will come over it; for no Lye is of the Truth<hi>:</hi> and though thou boaſts of a better Foundation then thoſe thou accuſeſt, yet all in the Light know the Devil is the Foundation and Author of every lye; but who are in the Light, and build upon the Light, are come to him that is the true Foundation of Generations too, and of which Prophets and Apoſtles bare teſtimony, and is now teſtified, that <hi>God was Light, and in him was no darkneſs at all;</hi> ſo Life and Truth is over Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and falſhood; this is our Foundation that have not cryed up any Light, but Chriſt that Corner-Stone that grinds to powder all that it falls upon: and in page 11. thou goeſt on to ſpeak of Chriſt's Church, we having ſaid it was his body, as though thou wouldſt contradict that Truth as well as others, ſayſt it is <hi>but his members for whom he layed down his Life; but this heady notion being altogether,</hi> (ſayeſt thou) <hi>condemned by Scripture, I ceaſe putting pen to paper in this matter:</hi> what thou meaneſt by the heady notion, I well know not that, except thy own Accuſation that thou ſpeakeſt before; but if thou didſt apply it to thy precedent words, in ſaying, the Saints were but Members, in contradiction to thoſe that in truth ſay, his Church is his Body; for thou art the firſt that wouldſt make difference between the Members and the Body of Chriſt, that I have heard of; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſome as blind as thy ſelf have gone about to make him two bodies; but Members without a Body, as thou mak'ſt, <hi>(with a but)</hi> I never heard of before: but his fulneſs, that filleth all in all, is known to them, and them only that diſcern his Body ſpiritual indeed, and ſeen only with the ſpiritual eye, which being blinded in thy ſelf, thou wouldſt darken in others: And ſo thou goeſt on repeating ſome Scriptures; and then calling
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58809:11"/>
after thy wonted manner to ſee, that thou canſt not ſhow; and then again thou beginſt, and ſayeſt, thou giveſt us to know, <hi>that the Bedy of our Lord was humane;</hi> and when thou haſt gone on as well as thou canſt to prove the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> and Chriſt one; then thou goeſt to make a difference, <hi>for this man, of whom we ſpeak, is not the made Image of God, as was</hi> Adam, <hi>ſayeſt thou, but the expreſs Image of the Fathers Perſon:</hi> ſo having ſpoken of things thou under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands not; thou brings a Scripture that thou imagineſt would prove it, by which thou proveſt thy own ignorance, both of the day, and the Scripture, <hi>that thou art my beloved Son this day have I begotten thee,</hi> which was (ſayeſt thou) <hi>when the holy Ghoſt overſhadowed</hi> Mary: All that believe in the Light know the day of his begetting, <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw it, and was glad, <hi>David</hi> ſaw it, and teſtified of it hundreds of years before the Virgins Conception at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> So thou that wouldſt not have the Son of God begotten, till he was conceived of <hi>Mary,</hi> who art not only out of the Faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> but blinder then the Prieſts of the World; for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y have and do preach, for ought I know, that he was begot and begetting from all Eternity, and that the day of his Reſurection was propheſied of by theſe words, This day have I begotten thee; ſo thou haſt ſo much pored on the humane body (as thou calleſt it) that thou muſt bring forth a birth like thy conception in the dark<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but I think, there is but few that will bow to thy image, for thou canſt not give it a ſeeming life neither from Scripture nor Reaſon.</p>
            <p>And thou goeſt on, and ſayeſt, <hi>He calleth not God Father,</hi> as we; but how wilt thou prove it? no more then thy othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> imaginations: for Chriſt ſaith, My Father, and your Father, without making a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, but thou differs and denies it: But thou denieſt Chriſt, Prophets and Apoſtles words, if they will not ſure thy imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and bringeſt forth thy blaſphemous thoughts: for the Son, ſayſt thou, <hi>was from the Subſtance of the Father, which was not the Diety that was begotten;</hi> ſo by thy words, wouldſt thou make it appear, that the ſubſtance of God is not <hi>Diety nor Divine:</hi> O ſtop thy mouth thou imaginary man, that in confuſion and darkneſs wouldſt ſpeak of that which thou art ſhut out of<hi>!</hi> for the key of <hi>David</hi> thou haſt not, and ſo canſt not know the womb that bare him which was pure, nor the ſeed he took upon him, nor his begetting; for he, the Chriſt, was not conceived in ſin, as thou wert, nor as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58809:11"/>
thou imagineſt; ſo thou wert better be ſilent, then exerciſe thy ſelf in things to high for thee; for all that ſtrive againſt the Light muſt be ſhut up in darkneſs, as thou art: and ſo goeſt on in thy (twelf page) ſaying, <hi>God was in Chriſt reconciling;</hi> here thou haſt brought a Scripture to overthrow all thy former Doctrine, for then it is not the <hi>humane that reconciles,</hi> but God; and then thou goeſt on to repeat what Chriſt ſaith, <hi>had I not come into the World, you had had no ſin, but now your ſins remain, becauſe ye believe not on him whom God hath ſent; for I come a Light into the World:</hi> and this his coming thou wouldſt have only at that time at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as if he had not come before, or ſince. I would enquire of thee, Was there no ſin, nor ſins till Chriſt was manifeſt at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> for <hi>had I not come into the world, you had had no ſin:</hi> for the cauſe of all ſin was and is the not coming to him which ſaves from ſin, who was, and is, and is to come: and ſo he that was the Light ſaith, <hi>I am come a Light into the World,</hi> and the condemnation of the World was, and is, <hi>that men love darkneſs better then Light;</hi> becauſe they come not to the Light, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ins remain; and who refuſes the Light <hi>come not to him that they may have life,</hi> but in darkneſs and death read and talk of the Scriptures, as thou doeſt, that brings this Scripture, that ſat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, <hi>God was in Chriſt reconciling the World to himſelf, and that Chriſt ſaith, I am come a Light into the World;</hi> ſeeming thereby to prove, that Chriſt was begotten that day the holy Ghoſt overſhadowed <hi>Mary,</hi> and that <hi>in humanity or earthly, and not by Deity,</hi> as thou called it; and all this thou ſayeſt, to prove Chriſt is not the Light in the Conſcience, and then brings a Scripture where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am come a Light, and that if he had not come, they had had no ſin:</hi> ſo inſtead of proving thy humane earthly Doctrine, the Scripture proves, that the cauſe and ground of all ſin, from the entrance of tranſgreſſion to this day, is the not coming to, or believing in the Light; for here Chriſt condemns of Sin, and convinceth of Sin, becauſe of unbelief in that which condemned them, which was the Spirit or Light: So thou haſt brought Scriptures, that Chriſt ſaith, he is come a Light, to prove thy Humane againſt the Light; and it proves againſt thee, and for us that teſtifie of the Light.</p>
            <p>But thou ſayeſt in another place, Chriſt is not defuſive, that is I confeſs, a word that is neither Scripture, nor the Spirits Language: but if thou meaneſt, he is not within his people, how doth this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58809:12"/>
overthrow thee in this error, as in others? for the Light ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the inner-parts, as thou confeſſeſt; and <hi>I am come a Light,</hi> ſaith Chriſt: ſo thou ſeeſt the Scripture manifeſts thy darkneſs and error: ſo thou wouldſt have been more covered if thou hadſt brought no Scripture, but hadſt delivered thy Doctrine againſt Chriſt a Light in the Conſcience, and hadſt brought thy Teacher J. B. to have proved it: for ſo contrary to Scripture art thou, that in thy very following words, page 12. where Chriſt ſaith, I am come a Light, thou ſayeſt, <hi>You have it clear, and out of doubt, who it is that is the Saviour, and the Lord Chriſt, not the Light in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but he that died and roſe again</hi> &amp; this thou wouldſt ſeem to prove by the former words, where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am come a Light into the World, and if I had not come you had not had ſin:</hi> ſo that all whoſe eyes are not dark ſee thy weakneſs, and that the Scriptures are for us that love the Lord Chriſt, of whom the Scriptures declare, that ſay, he is a Light, and this has enlightened every man; and yet thou art offended at thoſe that ſay he is in the Conſcience, though thou ſayeſt Gods Habitation is there: but the Light, againſt which thou ſtriveſt, will wear out and deſtroy all thy vain imaginations, for it is everlaſting, and from Heaven, and muſt prevail over thy <hi>humane earthly Image;</hi> yet that man Chriſt Jeſus, all that learn of the Light in the Conſcience know and confeſs unto; and his Fleſh is Meat indeed, and his Blood is Drink indeed; and the World one day ſhall be judged by him: but this thou, nor none that are in the Night, ſtriving againſt the Light, know or believe<hi>:</hi> ſo as a Thief in the night will he come on all ſuch. But thou goeſt on with the repetition of a Scripture out of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> of a <hi>high Prieſt after the order of</hi> Melchiſedeck, <hi>to make interceſſion for us;</hi> but how contrary to thy purpoſe of proving thy <hi>humane Chriſt not to be begotten, till con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>to be the high Prieſt that makes interceſſion for all:</hi> the wiſe in heart can ſee, who have learned in the the Light that hath viſited us from above, what the order of <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> is, <hi>no fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, no mother, no beginning of dayes, nor end of Life, who lives for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to make interceſſion for all that comes to God by him:</hi> and this is the Chriſt of God, that thou, and all the Deſpiſers and Reſiſters of the Light are ignorant of, and ſo come not to God by him that is without beginning of dayes or end of life; but in the carnal comprehenſion would meaſure Heavenly things, and ſo brings
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58809:12"/>
forth earthly imaginations, and by this would come to God, by your own deviſings, as <hi>Babels</hi> Builders of old; Theeves, and Robbers, that leave the Door, and for ſuch he enterceeds not; but for all that comes by him that is without beginning of dayes or end of life, he lives to make interceſſion, even for all that in Truth and Spirit Worſhip, and by the Spirit of Truth are lead into all Truth; ſuch that have abiding in, and teſtifie of that, are come to the myſtery of Faith held in the pure Conſcience<hi>:</hi> but this the Image-makers are ignorant of, as thou that wouldſt ſet up <hi>an invented Light of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Soul, for a Habitation of Reſt for God, and thoſe that God hath given to Chriſt;</hi> in which thou haſt bewrayed thy own ignorance of the Reſt of God, and his people, which the obedient and profiting ſervants enter into, even the joy of the Maſter, even the Glory of the Father, which was before the world was; &amp; this is not from the Earrh, nor of the Earth, but before the Earth was: and ſo <hi>the Light &amp; Spirit of the human Soul that thou ſetteſt up, as created to be a Habitation for God, and thoſe that God will give to Chriſt,</hi> will be thine, &amp; thy diſciples burthens, in the day that you will moſt ſtand in need of Reſt: but to proceed, thou goeſt on with thy own words, and ſome Scriptures that may eaſily, by all that can ſee, come over thy darkneſs, and is as though thy ſelf hadſt had a glimring of thy own darkneſs, and wert afraid of the blowes or ſmitings due to thee, and ſo to ſave thy head, goeſt on in words, as if thou meaneſt to undo all thou hadſt done; ſaying, <hi>thou muſt not be traduced by thoſe that trade in corrupted mens words, to the hindring of the paſſage of the Truth:</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I take notice of thy following words, I have ſomething to ſay to theſe: who thou mean'ſt by traders in corrupted mens words, I know not; but ſome have bin conſtrained, as I at this time, not to hinder the paſſage of Truth, but for Truths ſake; to bring forth the Truth over ſuch like corrupt words and writings as thine are; that the Truth may ſtand upon the head of deceit, that turnes every way to ſave it ſelf, as thou doeſt in thy following words, when after thou haſt brought forth ſo many accuſations againſt thoſe that cry up the Light, and borrow'd ſo many Scriptures with thy own private interpretations, to make truth thy ſeeming falſhood, and to ſet up thy own ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary light: After all and much more to this purpoſe, as if thou means thy ſelf, (like the fooliſh woman) to pull down thy own houſe, thou beginneſt to preach in words, the ſame that in words and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58809:13"/>
writings thou publickly haſt ſo appeared againſt; ſaying, <hi>This writing is not to draw the mind forth from waiting within it ſelf, for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of God in it ſelf, for that which is to be known of God is to be revealed in man:</hi> I anſwer, if that which is to be known of God be manifeſt in man, is it not in the conſcience? and is not that Light, that manifeſts? and doth not Chriſt ſay he is the Light? and doth any bring to the Father but Chriſt? and is any appointed to be hearkened unto for Life and Salvation, but Chriſt? and thou confeſſeſt, in the Apoſtles words, that <hi>what is to be known of God is manifeſt in man;</hi> and can any reveal the Father but the Son? which, thou ſayeſt, <hi>thou wouldſt not have any drawn forth from heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to that which manifeſts:</hi> which is that, and that only that the worſhipers of the true God teſtifie of and to; and if this thou wouldſt not have any drawn forth from, what meaneſt thy invented ſtory, of a created Habitation within, and the Light of a human Soul? ſo thou muſt confeſs thou haſt been ſetting up other lords to attend to, then the Lords Chriſt, or elſe with us in the Truth, that <hi>Chriſt only gives the knowledg of God in man;</hi> but thy windings to and fro manifeſts what root bares thee: ſo I not meaning to ſay any thing farther to thy twelf page, who ends it with few of thy own words, or thy Teacher <hi>Beamon,</hi> I ſhall go on to thy 13th page, where thou ſayeſt, <hi>that the promiſe is to the inward man of the heart, being quickned by the holy Ghoſt:</hi> to this I anſwer, God is not divided, whereever the Spirit is, Chriſt is, and of him have and do the Witneſſes of the Light teſtifie the ſame yeſterday to day and forever, the gift of the Father, that was never known nor learned, but in the meaſure of his own Spirit, as any may read, when Chriſt was viſible amongſt them at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and diſcourſed with the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> he did not call her ſo much to the beholding of his viſible Appearance or Perſon, as to know the gift of God, whereby ſhe could only have the knowledg who he was; and though he was preſent, he doth not ſay, believe in this Perſon at any time; but <hi>believe in the Light, that you may be Children of the Light:</hi> and when he came (that thou readeſt of) that ſaid, <hi>Good maſter, what ſhall I do that I may inherit eternal Life?</hi> he doth not ſay come, handle and feel this Perſon; but, ſaith he, <hi>why calleſt thou me good? there is none good but God;</hi> for Chriſt knew then, and now, none could ſell all for him, but who in Spirit lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58809:13"/>
him to be God bleſſed forever; and therefore he knew his going from them was expedient, that the promiſe of the Father's Spirit of Life might be more fully poured out upon them, in which he promiſed <hi>to be with them to the end of the world;</hi> and all that have Faith in the Gift of God, which is Eternal Life, free unto every creature, are witneſſes thereof, and the Reſurrection of this Light and Truth hath and doth torment the whole World of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that have or are hunting in the many ways, from the one thing needful, the Kingdom, Power and Spirit in them: yea, in the <hi>Heathen,</hi> at which the profeſſing Idolaters rage, though the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in which they truſt, teſtifie of it, that the very Crucifiers of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus had the <hi>Kingdom in them;</hi> and ſo from they 12fth page to thy 15th, I have little to meddle with of thy ſtolen words, <hi>of an in-eye and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal root, and of the ſtirring of the center,</hi> which all that have read <hi>Jacob Beamon</hi>'s myſterious miſt of imaginations, knows where thou hadſt them: though thou wouldſt make people believe they were thy own, and ſo nameſt not thy A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thours, as honeſt Writers uſe to do: but letting all that paſs, and thy ſo often repeating, as formerly, <hi>the Light of Conſcience is not the Chriſt:</hi> I anſwer, I never knew any but thee ſay it was; ſo it ſeems thou haſt been a confuting thy ſelf, hoping thereby to confound others; but the Light only ſhews that in us, is not of us; but to the blind all is alike, elſe ſurely thou wouldſt not after all thy Arguments and framed Reaſons to draw the mind from the Light within, to eye the Perſon without, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and deſtroy thy own Doctrine, by ſaying, <hi>my intent in this wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is not to draw the mind forth from waiting within it ſelf, for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of God in it ſelf; for that which is to be known of God is to be revealed in man:</hi> what, will the Scriptures (think'ſt thou by thy wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, adding and diminiſhing) ſerve thee to prove or diſprove, as thou wouldſt have it? ſure all that have an eye ſee thee, that haſt deny'd <hi>the Light within to be either God, Chriſt, or his Principle, and yet would have them wait within for it:</hi> what then wouldſt thou have them wait on? thou talkeſt indeed of a Sword <hi>that God had ſet in the human Soul, to keep the way of the Tree of Life;</hi> then <hi>Robert</hi> is the Tree of Life, where the human Soul is, and yet neither Chriſt nor his Principle: and in the ſixth page thou ſayeſt, <hi>there is a Light in man that is the Habitation of God;</hi> and in thy fourteenth page, <hi>that God hath choſen the heart of man for his Habitable Place:</hi> ſo it ſeems
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58809:14"/>
the Light thou ſpeakeſt of, and mans heart in thy ſence are one; and <hi>wouldſt thou have man wait within his own heart,</hi> from whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds all manner of evil; for thou concludeſt it <hi>is mans duty to wait in his heart for the promiſe of the Father, and yet neither Chriſt nor his Principle there,</hi> as thou ſaiſt; and ſo if thou know'ſt another thing to he waited on, or to open the heart then Chriſt, thou ſhouldſt have declared it; for the internal Root, what is it? or that which can bring into the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> if not Chriſt? then thou haſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther root to be brought to or wait on, then the Chriſt of God, or to lead then he, it is an Idol: So thou that haſt been ſo long crying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them that preach up the Light within the way to God, <hi>cryes up an internal root, an in-man of the heart, and what not,</hi> ſo thou mayſt keep from <hi>the one thing needful,</hi> in the many things: Oh how vain is man in his imaginations, and that continually! witneſs this precedent relation of R. C. that would ſet up any thing of his own or others inventions, to draw from the one ſafe, ſure, and unalterable Way of Life; and which all that are come to, and have life in, cannot but teſtifie that it is almighty, and in the ſtrength thereof, as we receive, muſt teſtifie againſt all and every one that would deceive, or draw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide by ſubtil diviſing and craftineſs of men, to blind the eye of the mind, preſents <hi>that there is other wayes and means to be looked to, and to be waited on, then the only begotten of God,</hi> which alone hath been teſtified of, and witneſſed to by us that have learned of the Light, and therin received the earneſt and aſſurance of a Kingdom that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſhaken; the ſure rock againſt which Hells ſtrength ſhall never prevail: And ſo knowing aſſuredly that he is in us that ſaves from ſin, and his name is <hi>Jeſus,</hi> cannot but teſtifie againſt all Images, and their makers; for unto him alone is our eye, that is from everlaſting to everlaſting, that in the fulneſs of time took fleſh upon him, and dwelt amongſt us, and this is our Light, our Life, our Root, Spirit and Power; and ſhall wear out all created lights, imagined internal roots, and natures light, with all R. C's and others imaginations, who not being able to get from under the Righteous Judgments of God, goes about to ſpeak evil of the things he knoweth not; and ſo the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural light, and the ſpirit of a man &amp; the light of Conſcience, or what the carnal man can ſee and know, being his own, he brings forth, and ſaith, theſe are our opinions; ſo in the Truth muſt all lyes and falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood be turned on the head of the lyar, from whence they come, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58809:14"/>
in Truth are we eſtabliſhed more and more, having no God but one, and he everlaſting and almighty; <hi>who commanded Light taſhine out of darkneſs, and hath ſhined in our hearts to give us the Light of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Glory of himſelf in the face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and this is that I had of the Lord to give forth as a teſtimony againſt R. C. his paper, entituled <hi>God's Truth atteſted according to Scripture,</hi> about 8. months ſince, and about that time was it written; but having the knowledg that a brother (whom in the Lord I honour for his faithful continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſervice in and for God's Truth's ſake) was anſwering of it, I laid theſe my papers aſide not knowing a uſe for them, not looking on them, as I know, for ſeven months time; but about three weeks ſince, or thereabouts, looking among my writings, I lighted on them, and had ſomething, as I was reading them, in my heart, that it muſt be publiſhed.</p>
            <p>But not at that inſtant giving up clearly to it, the next night, or the next after, the Lord viſited me with a ſore and dangerous Diſtemper of body, and I being an ancient woman, that have and do wait for my change, received it as a Meſſenger for my removal out of this Tabernacle of clay; and not at all grievous unto me, having by obedience to, and by Faith in the Light obtained redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of that which muſt come to an end, and an entrance into the Life and Kingdom that ſhall never have end: ſo waiting quietly on my weak bed for the revelation of his will whom I ſerve in my ſpirit day and night, what his will and pleaſure was to do with me, for I have learned that its better to live to God, then to have a life in this World: and whilſt I thus waited, my ſleep being ſhort, I had in them ſeveral ſights of ſomthing I was to ſuffer and do in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World, among which a ſight of a late work of R. C. in which he would beſpatter the ſervant or ſervants of the Lord; and the morning after this Viſion, one came in and related to me, that R. C. had ſent his Queries out to G. F. and his miniſters, but G. F's life is where the evil one, nor any of his miniſters can come; ſent of God, Bleſt, and a Bleſſing to the Generation of the Righteous: Then the Lord clear'd it to me, that what I had writ, or ſhould farther be given in unto me, as to or of R. C. to give forth, and then an aſſurance I had of being healed of my weakneſs, and declared it to one Friend, that the Lord had ſomthing more for me to do ere I went hence, &amp; if but this, in bearing teſtimony againſt this Inſtrument of the evil one,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58809:15"/>
I ſhall lye down in peace, for I ſpeak the truth, I lye not, the Lord in a Viſion by night, afore ever I ſaw R. C. in the outward, ſhewed me him, and his dwelling and family, in the night ſeaſon, and that he ſhould be a Troubler of the Houſe of God and cauſe his people to ſuffer; and I have ſeen and traced him in his work, and am well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his outſide love &amp; feigning whereby he hath deceived ſome ſimple in his pretended ſingularity and elocution of his own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine &amp; way: and though he long walked with us, yet never came to the knowledg of the Truth; and the old bottle being unbroken, ſuch as he had, &amp; hath, he brings forth of it, and has by cunning led ſome ſilly ones captive by perverting the good way of God; yea, ſo proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous has he been in his curſed practice among thoſe that were willing again to imbrace this preſent world, that he has perverted whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, that were called with the high and heavenly Call, but never come to the election; and ſo have been deceived, and are found ſuch as have taken the name of God in vain, and are not, nor ſhall not be held guiltleſs; and though they have or may make merry over the ſlain, perverters and perverted from the good way of the Lord, yet their Condemnation ſlumbers not, and the Lord hath and doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their wicked works, that having betrayed the Truth in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, would tempt others to believe a lye, as if we were like unto themſelvs, &amp; looked for Salvation by another way, then by Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the Son of God: ſo that none may believe a lye is this ſent abroad, that he, and he <hi>only</hi> of whom the Scriptures declare is our Salvation, and there is not another way to God; and what is recorded of him, and by him in the Scriptures of Truth, from the firſt of <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the laſt of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> knowing that they were given forth as holy men were moved of the holy Ghoſt, &amp; not of a private interpretation for the unlearned of this Spirit, have and do interpret to their own deſtruction; for none have ſeen God at any time but the only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and they to whom he reveals him, and by ſpirit only was and is made manifeſt, and that a meaſure of this is given to every one to profit withal, the Scriptures bear witneſs; and this, and no other is their Principle that are called <hi>Quakers;</hi> and by Faith we have profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, dwelling in this Light and Spirit, know the blood of Jeſus which clenſeth from all ſin, and gives us fellowſhip with the Father and Son, in the meaſure of this Spirit that hath filled our hearts with love and good will unto all; and ſo with the hazard of all this World hath,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58809:15"/>
through ſufferings, accuſations and bad reports we paſs, ſounding forth the good-will of God unto every one, that he hath given a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his own Spirit to profit withal; and they that will not hearken unto it, will not believe though one from the dead ſhould be ſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; &amp; this is that which was given unto me to be ſent forth as an anſwer, and to come over the imagined doctrines of R. C. in his firſt paper, that is called <hi>the Truth at teſted according to Scripture,</hi> but is found contrary to Scripture and Truth, and by us teſtified againſt, that have cryed up no light but that which he that was ſent of God bears witneſs to, Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Theſe following Lines were added ſince</hi> Robert Cobbits <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries came to my hand; and it is manifeſt, his own Work therein, hath and ſhall inſnare him.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have read or heard of a Tyrannical Perſecutor, that among other cruelties invented to deſtroy the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and one was, to have them rent in pieces with wild Beaſts, and to make the Beaſts more eager of their prey, would clothe the men deſigned for death in Beaſts skins: that which brought this to my remembrance, is, the late works of <hi>R. C.</hi> and one that writes her ſelf <hi>E. A.</hi> they being in the ſame deſign as the Tyrant was, to hinder the increaſe of Truth, and to make the obedient thereto odious to all honeſt hearted people, that are afraid of falſe gods and worſhips, by declaring that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called <hi>Quakers</hi> ſet up a Light to be truſted in, and learned of, and ſay, it is God and Chriſt; and then make a relation of ſuch a light as they have invented, which they call by many names, and as far as I underſtand by ſeveral natures, as in reading their writings any may ſee: ſaying, that the <hi>Light is the ſpirit of a man,</hi> and the <hi>light of a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſoul,</hi> and a <hi>formed light,</hi> and the <hi>light of nature,</hi> and the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> and the <hi>worm that never dies;</hi> and yet alſo, that is <hi>a Habitation or Dwelling for God, and thoſe that he hath given to Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> with many more ſuch expreſſions of the inſufficiency and badneſs of their imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned light; and then again of the excellency of it, to and fro, for and againſt; babble indeed: and all this to make people believe that we call to ſuch a light as they imagine, and have ſet up in their own brains (and that we believe not in Chriſt the true Light) which manner of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58809:16"/>
light (which they would have people believe we preach up) is their own, and the burthen thereof, which they would lay upon the Lord's people, ſhall turn upon themſelves; and the ſnare they laid ſhall take them, and the leaſt of the many thouſands of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> know their light is darkneſs; and thouſands with me can witneſs, that have conſtantly walked for theſe thirteen years, with theſe people, (that theſe Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of envy and ſtrife are riſen up againſt) and that in all our time, we never heard of any ſuch light as they declare of to be truſted in; nay, I am bold to ſay many thouſands amongſt us never heard of a formed light, to be a dwelling place for God, and thoſe he will give Chriſt, much leſs have we believed in ſuch a created lye: I anſwer for the Lord and his choſen, and in his preſence that ſearches every heart, that I am perſwaded that thouſands of theſe people, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> would lay down their lives, rather then ever confeſs or bow to ſuch a Light as R. C's and E. A's, whom I am willing to joyn together, for they have joyned in one iniquity; yet there is not much danger that her work will hurt any, as her ſelf, being ſo contradictive in it ſelf, and to him that is in the ſame work with her, to call that which R. C. calls, The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Chriſt, and Gods Dwelling, <hi>the Tree of Knowledge,</hi> and in this confuſion calls the Quakers <hi>Myſtery Babylon:</hi> and ſo all may ſee, that give heed to the true Light, how theſe Perverters have gone about to clothe the true Worſhippers in their idolatrous and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous invented errors, that, by a Lye, they might keep from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the Truth, which all the Worſhippers in the Spirit of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus are led into; and never did the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſince the day of their firſt coming forth to this day, declare of any other Light, then the <hi>Spirit of Jeſus, that Word of God, that was with God before the World was made,</hi> that as a <hi>two-edged Sword, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides between Soul and Spirit;</hi> but who of this Word have not learned, ſets up that ſpirit (that is to be divided from) for the Word, and for the Light; here the Myſtery of Iniquity entred, and is upheld to this day, in a pretence of God, Antichriſt ſetting mans ſpirit above all that is called God, as God, Chriſt, and his Spirit, ſets up a likeneſs, or the ſpirit of man, to draw from the one Spirit that can only lead into Truth; and the obedient there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto declare, as they have learned, <hi>that by obedience to the Spirit the Soul comes to be ſanctified</hi> and ſeparated, as ſaith the Apoſtle
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58809:16"/>
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> from all that ſeparates from God; but the Apoſtle did not ſay this of the Spirit of the Humane Soul, or the Light of Nature, but of the <hi>Eternal Spirit that raiſed Jeſus from the dead, and hath quickned your mortal bodies,</hi> and this is the Light and Life that we have declared of, the <hi>Spirit of Life that ſets free from ſin and death,</hi> not divided from, but proceeding of Father and Son; but of this R. C. and E. A. are not learned, as may be ſeen by their imaginations of the Light and Spirit of Chriſt, which the People of God, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> have teſtified of; but were it not for a full aſſurance I have, that ſhe and R. C. whom I am called to plead againſt, are Fighters againſt God, I ſhould never have waded in ſuch durt as they have brought forth; but being on my heart, as an addition to what I have eight months ſince writ to R. C's firſt, now to ſpeak a little to his many Queries, I writ this as a preface thereto; not ſo much for his ſake do I writ, (though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly I wiſh he might find a place of repentance) as for others whom he is ſeeking to betray; and as the ſcope of his firſt work was to perſwade people we preached of a falſe Light and Chriſt, even ſuch a one as he imagined; ſo in theſe his Queries he would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuatingly, by asking queſtions, and perverting the words of Truth that have formerly been given forth, perſwade the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as if we denied Chriſt Jeſus, of whom the Scriptures teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie: And though I have no life in contention, but have and do labour in all things to avoid ſuch queſtions as gender to ſtrife, yet having faln on the vain janglings, and unprofitable words that he hath filled his paper with (for which he ſhall ſurely be called to an account, with all other his idle words) and though it be not my purpoſe to be large in the matter; though in every Query, and all his other words therein, he manifeſts his folly and envy therein, with his vain repetitions, and unprofitable queſtions, and may all be turned upon his head; yet I ſhall only take a perticular no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of ſome few of them, with ſome of the Lyes he charges the Lords people with, and the wicked and blaſphemous imaginations he hath of the Son of God, and anſwer to him, as our Saviour did to the ſubtil Generation that came by queſtions to inſnare him, who inſtead of anſwering, gave them a queſtion which they durſt not anſwer, neither would he give an anſwer to them, neither ſhould I, nor any of the Lord's people, (that have learned why we came into the World, and cannot ſpend our time here unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58809:17"/>
but muſt anſwer the will of him that ſent us, that we may render our account with joy) ever have put pen to paper to have anſwered R. C's firſt or laſt impertinent or falſe matters, if not called of the Lord, for his Truth ſake, and your ſakes that may be hindred, or hurt, or kept out of the Way of Peace, where we have found him whom our ſouls love, and cannot but teſtifie of his good will unto all that his hands have made, and that you may believe the Truth.</p>
               <p>For no other Way, Means nor Name did we ever find Salvation by, or declare to be believed in for Redemption and everlaſting Life, then the Son of God; and that was and is he of whom the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures declare, without any cover or deceit, as our enemy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates that he may deceive; but in plainneſs before the great God that ſearches every heart, and has and will Judge in Righteouſneſs every falſe Speaker; no other Chriſt have we faith in, or teſtifie of, then he that was conceived by the holy Ghoſt in the Virgins womb, and brought forth in the fulneſs of time, as it was prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied of, and was carryed into <hi>Egypt</hi> to be ſaved from <hi>Herod,</hi> that pretended to worſhip, but went to murder the Child <hi>Jeſus:</hi> This was he that made a good confeſſion before <hi>Pilate,</hi> and was ſlain by wicked hands, but it was impoſſible that Death ſhould keep him under, ſo he roſe and declared unto the woman that was a witneſs of his Reſurrection that he aſcended, and gave her command to declare to others; and ſo whatever the Scriptures, that were given forth by the holy Spirit declare of Chriſt Jeſus, his body, his Suffering, and Riſing, and his Aſcenſion, we believe; and he <hi>is aſcended far above all Heavens that he may fill all things;</hi> who was and is <hi>the everlaſting God, the mighty Counſeller, the Prince of Peace;</hi> yet this I nor any ever knew ſavingly (whatever we have heard or read of it) but as it came to be revealed in us by his own Spirit, which was the promiſe of the Father, of the Son, that were and are one forever; and (though R. C. blaſphemouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denies it) he pours forth his Spirit on his Sons, and on his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and this is the Covenant, that <hi>they ſhould not depart from him,</hi> but <hi>be taught of him;</hi> and this was it the Apoſtles ſpake of, That <hi>a meaſure was given to profit withal,</hi> and more we know not of God, nor Chriſt, then of this we learn; and as we receive thereof, we give to others, and all that believe therein find profiting thereby, and are brought into the plain Way, and feel their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58809:17"/>
Redemption thereby, and <hi>Jeſus</hi> with them, that <hi>ſaves from ſin,</hi> and ſo can no longer worſhip Idols, and ſo all Image-makers come to be tormented, from him that ſits at <hi>Rome,</hi> to the leaſt of all the Harlots brood; for of her they are, and in her ſorceries, that imagine and ſets up any thing to be looked to or truſted in for Life and Salvation, but Jeſus Chriſt, which is only received and known by his own Spirit: And this is the doctrine of the people called <hi>Quakers</hi> from firſt to this preſent day, and forever, at which all Image-makers rage and are tormented, that their <hi>Diana</hi>'s muſt come down; and among which R. C. ſtrugles that his may have a place to be; for though he could never ſtoop to obedience of Truth, yet he feels and knows it ſhakes his images as well as others, and fearing the falling thereof makes lyes his refuge; but the Truth has and ſhall come over all, and my deſire is even to the God of my hope (that is Light, and in him is no darkneſs at all) that the honeſt in heart may receive this Teſtimony, and it is true, that what ever has been given forth by Prophets, Chriſts mouth, or the Apoſtles, or any ſent of God concerning or of the Son of God, we believe, but deny and witneſs againſt all the imaginations of the comprehending mind, that meaſures heavenly things in the earthly carnal minde, that never could diſcern the things of God; ſo in this from firſt to laſt has the myſtery of iniquity wrought, and been brought forth, talking of the fleſh and blood of Jeſus, yet never come to eat thereof, nor to know an effectual cleanſing thereby, but offering deſpite unto the Spirit of Grace which brings Salvation, and whilſt they are talking of the Blood that was ſhed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they trample the Blood of the new Covenant under foot, from the Mother of Harlots to the leaſt of her falſe begotten Children, among which R. C. is to be teſtified againſt; and the call of the Lord is to come out from all their Sorceries, the images and likeneſſes of heavenly things; to the Subſtance, Power and Life, that the Lord in this our day has viſited us with, the day-ſpring from on high, the Hope of the Righteous in all Generations, that, many are come to partake of, and receive Life, the Life that ſhall never have an end; this is by the Spirit of Life: So bleſſed be all and every one that hath an ear to hear what the Spirit ſaith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:58809:18"/>
               <head>R. C.</head>
               <p>I Have lookt over thy many Queries, and finding them unprofitable not tending to the edification of any (but to ſtir up ſtriſe) ſo I ſaid in my heart, <hi>If thou hadſt believed the Scriptures, or underſtood the words of Truth that hath often been ſounded in thy ears, thou hadſt never asked ſuch Queſtions;</hi> ſome of which thou knowſt we never denied; and hadſt thou ever come to the <hi>one thing</hi> in which there is no Error, thou hadſt not ſo run into the <hi>many things,</hi> in which all err; and though thy darkneſs be great (as all muſt be that would have the knowledg of God and heavenly things by any other way, then the Spirit of Chriſt) yet I have cauſe to fear that in the <hi>Spirit that luſts to envy,</hi> thou charges that upon us, that thou doeſt not believe we are guilty of, for thou hearing us ſo many years only to teſtifie of the one thing, <hi>the Gift of God,</hi> and <hi>the Spirit of Jeſus,</hi> that <hi>faithful and true Witneſs,</hi> that <hi>was with God in the beginning;</hi> and never hearing any that bear teſtimony to or for the Light, ſpeak of any other for Salvation, but the <hi>only begotten of God;</hi> couldſt thou think we meant any other, that thou ſhouldſt deviſe ſo many errors and falſe Opinions to place on us, and yet not be able to bring any of our words or writings (that ſo many years together thou wert ſo converſant with) to prove that we ever cryed up any ſuch things as thou charges us with? (what will the end be of wilful ſinning) didſt thou ever hear us ſet up or call to any witneſs, but the <hi>Spirit of Chriſt?</hi> and thou beginſt thy Queries of <hi>a witneſs that we affirm to be God and Chriſt;</hi> and I anſwer, ſo we do, that faithfull and true one, that made all things, and we have this witneſs in our ſelves; and is it honeſty in thee to ſay this is but the <hi>ſpirit of a man?</hi> it is like that the Witneſs thou witneſſeth with is a falſe ſpirit, but ours is the true; thou ſhouldſt not <hi>ſpeak evil of that thou knowſt not;</hi> for thou art as unknowing it ſeems of what we declare as unbelieving, that calls the Spirit or Witneſs we declare of, <hi>the Worm that never dyes;</hi> what, no difference R. in the dark I ſee; what wouldſt thou have God and Divil one?
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58809:18"/>
that I hear indeed, is the Ranters principle, which thou in this ſeems to be one with: what, no difference between him that judges in Righteouſneſs, and he that accuſes? all that can be ſaid in this matter for thee, is, that <hi>thou haſt more knowledg of the Worm that never dyes then of him we believe in;</hi> but how thou canſt make good thy former doctrine, that <hi>the Light in Conſcience ſhould be a Habitation for God,</hi> and thoſe that <hi>he has given to Chriſt,</hi> and yet ſhould be <hi>the Worm that never dyes,</hi> I know not; for we believe no ſuch confuſion; for thou might'ſt as well have ſaid Hell &amp; Heaven are one, and the Divil will never break the Serpents head, as that thou haſt ſaid, and theſe are thy own, for we teſtifie of no ſuch witneſs, but againſt that and thee that ſo invents, for we are joyned to, and believe in him, in whom the Accuſer hath no part. And in thy twelf page thou repeats ſome Scriptures that our Friends its like have put forth, which teſtifies to Truth; as theſe words, <hi>He that hath not the Spirit of Chriſt is none of his, and that none receives the Spirit but he that believes in Chriſt that is giver of the Spirit,</hi> to which thou addeſt theſe words as a Query, <hi>Whether the Spirit you walk by is the Spirit of Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>the power of Magick, Anſwer?</hi> to which I Anſwer, may not all that have an eye to ſee, ſee what ſpirit thou art of, that ſo much ſpeaks of Scripture, and when ſuch Scriptures are brought as ſmites thy Image, and teſtifies to the Truth, thou art ſo far from anſwering any thing in plainneſs to it, that thou tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt into a Query, whether <hi>our Spirit we walk by be the Spirit of Chriſt, or the ſpirit of Magick?</hi> O how do thy evil thoughts and imaginations gender to ſtrife, what ground haſt thou to queſtion this, but a lye of thy own framing? ſaying, <hi>we deny him to be the Chriſt that was the offering for ſin,</hi> which lye muſt turn upon thy own head, for he that did and doth live make to interceſſion for all that come to God by him we confeſs to, and there is no offering for ſin, but Jeſus, whom we witneſs to ſave from ſin: ſo for thy <hi>Magick</hi> and <hi>Sorcery,</hi> it is thy own, for we have no fellowſhip with them that work it, but know, that ſuch as withſtand the Truth (as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> by bringing forth likeneſſes of what <hi>Moſes</hi> wrought in and by the Finger and Arm of God) they that bring forth a likeneſs by their Sorceries, whereby the hearts of the Oppreſſors were hardened, and the Seed which God would have
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58809:19"/>
delivered kept the longer in bondage, and how deeply thou haſt been in this work of <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> thou wilt one day know.</p>
               <p>And many of thy Queries, yea, the moſt tending only to inſnare, in asking, <hi>if that Chriſt which was and did the things mentioned in Scriptures, be the Chriſt or Light in the Conſcience?</hi> to this I Anſwer thou art ſpeaking as one that hath many Gods and many Lords, but we who walk in the Light have but one God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and he and his Spirit is one; ſo he that ſaid to his Diſciples, that he <hi>which was with them</hi> (not divided) <hi>would be in them;</hi> ſo one God do the Children of Light confeſs to, made manifeſt by his Son in Spirit, and theſe are one; but thou in the ſecond page of thy Queries ſayeſt, <hi>Chriſt is not the Eternal Father,</hi> and that <hi>he and his Father is not one;</hi> and thy carnal Reaſon for it is, <hi>that he that gives is one,</hi> and <hi>he to whom it is given another,</hi> and this to prove or maintain Chriſt and God to be two; well mayeſt thou fight againſt us, and our words of Truth, that goes about to make void or diſprove the words of Chriſt, that ſaith, My Father and I are one, when he was in the Perſon thou ſo much ſpeak'ſt of; but thou ſayeſt they are two, and the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſays <hi>(John</hi> 1. 3.) <hi>all things were made by him, and without him was nothing made that was made;</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>all things were made by him and for him;</hi> but thou R. C. art not aſhamed to deny the words of the Apoſtles, and ſayeſt plainly, <hi>all things were not made by him,</hi> thou blaſphemouſly going to comprehend the things of God in thy dark mind, denies the words of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And in thy nineth page ſayſt, I ſee not wherein you are wronged in being charged to deny God and Chriſt, in a Place, above Sun, Moon, and Stars, and Elements; nay, it is like thou doſt not, nor will not ſee our wrong, that art ſo great a Wronger of us, that in ſo many years as thou watched us with an evil eye, yet not having from our own words, to charge us of error or evil, comes forth as publickly as thou canſt to ſet the World againſt us, by telling them we cry up and worſhip ſuch a light as thou haſt invented, and thou mighteſt as truly have ſaid, that we denied God any where as that thou had ſaid; but let Truth come over all thy former Lyes, as this, God being our Witneſs that we lye not, but have and do
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58809:19"/>
confeſs before men, that our Lord is above and over all created things, the Earth, the Heavens, and all therein, the works of his Hands in whom we believe, <hi>God bleſſed for evermore,</hi> whoſe <hi>Throne is Heaven above all, and the Earth his Foot-ſtool,</hi> and under his Feet ſhall all his Enemies be put, then will every Image-makers be brought down, and every Lyars mouth be ſtoped, and falſe Accuſer; and he that invents wrong ſhall have no place, but that which is prepared for him.</p>
               <p>And in thy nineth page thou Querieſt, <hi>if the Chriſt, which</hi> John <hi>ſaid was the Chriſt, or the Light in man be the Chriſt, which G. F. ſaith is the Chriſt; explain,</hi> ſayſt thou: To which I Anſwer, without guile in the Truth, I have known G. F. as thou neither haſt nor canſt know him, while thou fighteſt againſt the true Light, and thouſands can witneſs, that of God he was ſent, to bear witneſs of the ſame <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> bear witneſs to; and there is but one Chriſt what ever thou imagins, <hi>in whom was and is Life,</hi> and this <hi>Life is the Light of men,</hi> and <hi>this is the true Light which enlightens every man that comes into the World;</hi> but thou and all that love darkneſs better then Light, cannot comprehend the true Light, and ſo deſpiſeſt the Meſſengers thereof, growing in envy againſt them, as <hi>Cain</hi> againſt <hi>Abel</hi> that offered in Faith, and had this Teſtimony <hi>that he pleaſed God;</hi> but <hi>Cain</hi> in the unbelief grows angry, and riſes againſt his brother; and ſo thoſe who through the unbelief, loving darkneſs better then Light, riſe up againſt the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of Light, if it be Apoſtles, or G. F. or who ever, as thou R. C. do'ſt, who deny'ſt <hi>John's</hi> words, that ſaith, <hi>All was made by him</hi> (the word Chriſt) and thou plainly ſayeſt it is not ſo; <hi>for he did not make himſelf,</hi> (ſayeſt thou) ſo none will marvel thou canſt not ſee nor receive G. F's teſtimony of Chriſt, that cannot receive <hi>John's</hi> teſtimony; yet no other Chriſt then he that gave life for all men hath G. F. teſtified of, and we know he lives for ever, and he and his [mark] no comprehender knows, who was from eternity to eternity; and though <hi>in the days of his humiliation his Judgments was taken from him, who can declare his generation?</hi> not thou, which vainly asks <hi>what is become of him the Chriſt which the Scriptures declare of:</hi> to which is anſwered, he is every where, (and all things are upheld by him) and in us of a truth, that in his Light have
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58809:20"/>
believed: But thou and all that in the imaginations of your own hearts, are ſtiving againſt the Spirit of Grace, cannot wait for or diſcern his appearance, and therefore ask <hi>what is become of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in thy eleventh page thou Querieſt, <hi>Whether</hi> Peters <hi>witneſs in his Conſcience, by which he confeſſed Chriſt to be the Son of God, was not as much God and Chriſt, as the Witneſs in you?</hi> I Anſwer, Chriſt told Peter, <hi>It was the Spirit of his Father,</hi> and Chriſt's anſwer hath and doth ſatisfie all that believe in him, and that <hi>Father, Son, and Spirit are one;</hi> which then did and now do ſpeak in us that believe, to the torment of all vain imaginers, as art thou, that asks if the witneſs in us be any other then that in <hi>Peter,</hi> which Chriſt bears teſtimony to, and that to him; but thou ſayſt the witneſs is the Worm that ſhall never dyes. This was the Spirit that called the Maſter of the houſe <hi>Belzebub,</hi> that makes a ſlight thing of the Spirit of the Father, as if leſs then God or Chriſt, by which we that believe are ſaved, and have fellowſhip with the Father and Son, and all that are in the Light, where the blood is witneſſed, which takes away all ſin; and of it, and to this Spirit we witneſs, that thou in thy firſt page ſayſt, <hi>it is the Spirit of a man, and the Worm that never dyes,</hi> and <hi>that againſt our doctrine thou muſt teſtifie:</hi> So repent of thy blaſphemies if thou canſt, it is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the Living God: but to draw to a concluſion of ſpeaking much more to thy Queries, the moſt being but repetitious of the like unprofitable ſtuff, I ſhall a little take notice of what thou ſayſt to them thou calleſt thy <hi>old friends,</hi> (and if I have not fully anſwered, yet I have given thee what is given unto me, and am clear; it ſhall ſtop thy wicked purpoſe, and the Lord hath many valiant Souldiers for his Truth, that ſhall yet ſmite every enemy that riſes up againſt the Faith, till your Chariot-wheels be ſtruck off, and you all ſwallowed in the deep, who do what you can to ſtop <hi>Iſrael</hi> in his way; but Hells ſtrength ſhall not prevail againſt our Rock Chriſt, revealed in Spirit, receive it if thou canſt) and thy old Friends, as thou calleſt them, thou goeſt on to ſpeak to, whom thou ſayeſt, <hi>thou wouldſt not have fall ſhort of entring the Reſt;</hi> and then urges it by a lye; but if they were dreaming of ſuch a Reſt as thou imagins, and in thy firſt Book calls it <hi>a Dwelling place for God</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:58809:20"/>
                  <hi>and his people,</hi> and in theſe thy Queries, the <hi>Worm that ſhall never dyes,</hi> which it will be well for all to fall ſhort: but whom doeſt thou account thy Friends among us, if it were ſuch as knew thee, when thou appears to be that thou wert not, though they may pity thy ſoul, yet can they do leſs then abominate thy hypocritical practiſes, for ſo many years together that ſeemed to be, and wert not? and if to the plain hearted thou ſpeakeſt, that hates deceit and every evil way, thou wilt not by thy feigned words get any entrance; but if by the <hi>old Friend,</hi> thou meaneſt thoſe that once took the name and profeſſion of Truth in their mouthes, as much as thee or more, and by their own unbelieving hearts, and thine, or ſuch like Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayers, are drawn back, ſuch manifeſting they have taken the name of the Lord in vain, and the Lord will not hold them guiltleſs, for they have and do grieve his holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>And which of thy Reſts thou haſt preached to theſe I know not, but their obedience to thy Earthly ſpirit, they manifeſtly hold forth in their <hi>returning again to their vomit,</hi> and <hi>as Swine to wallow in their former Mire:</hi> the Miniſters of the Light and Grace of God, have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and do call out of the World, and the Cuſtoms and Faſhions thereof, to him that was not, nor is not of the World, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> but to whom haſt thou called, that haſt brought to <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Hair, Gold and Pearl, and boldneſs of Face,</hi> inſtead of ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faceneſs and modeſty, to cringings and bowings, worſhipping of Creatures inſtead of ſobriety and fear; and more might be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, if convenient, of thoſe thou haſt perverted from the Way of Truth and Honeſty; and theſe if they repent not, will not fall ſhort of thy Reſt, <hi>The Worm that ſhall never dye;</hi> and then thou giveſt an exhortation to <hi>beware that no man deceive you, for the Spirit foreſeeing what would be in the latter dayes, foretold a departure from the Faith, and that men ſhould riſe up, bringing in moſt damnable errors, and denying the Lord that bought them, and many ſhall follow their pernicious wayes, of whom the Way of Truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of;</hi> ſo thou draweſt to an end as thou begineſt; for as thou wouldſt have people believe that we worſhipped and believed in ſuch a god as thou imagin'ſt, and then placeſt concluſions on thy own invented doctrine, ſo the evil thou diviſeſt muſt fall upon thy ſelf; for here thou brings a Scripture, that there ſhould be a falling from the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58809:21"/>
Faith, and wouldſt place it on us, now that the evil ſpoken of by the Apoſtle is and doth come unto all that deny the faith, is true, but is it we or R. C. that have denied the Faith? let the wiſe in heart judge, for the Faith which the Scriptures ſpeak of, by which the Saints did <hi>overcome the World,</hi> but the Faith which R. C. hath preached, hath carried back into the World <note n="‖" place="margin">Know the Tree by the Fruit,</note> they that in meaſure were redeemed out of it, having again imbraced this preſent World, and they are ſuch as <hi>deny the Lord that bought them,</hi> even ſuch as the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks of, that like the <hi>firſt Angels,</hi> that <hi>kept not their firſt ſtate,</hi> and <hi>likewiſe that kept not their Habitations,</hi> but <hi>deſpiſes Dominion,</hi> and <hi>ſpeaks evil of Dignities,</hi> ſo theſe ſpeak evil of thoſe things they know not; but what they naturally knows as bruit Beaſts; now is not this R. C. and his Diſciples (that have riſen up againſt the Dignities that are from above) running into the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and periſhing in the gainſaying of <hi>Corah;</hi> has not his envy made it manifeſt? O forget not, for as it was ſpoken it is come to paſs, the <hi>Earth hath ſwollowed up many of you,</hi> and <hi>none ſhall eſcape that diviſe againſt the Worſhip in Truth and Spirit,</hi> and ſets up a <hi>formed Light,</hi> and <hi>natural Light to be the dwelling of God and his people that he has given to Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> So thou art manifeſted to know nothing, but what thou knoweſt naturally, as a bruit Beaſt, and ſo appointeſt a natural reſt, for thoſe that believe thy doctrine, and warns thy <hi>old Friends, not to fall ſhort of it,</hi> for it ſeems thou knoweſt not another then what thou knoweſt naturally; but they who are come to <hi>the Law of the Spirit of Grace, that ſets free from ſin and death,</hi> know there is a Reſt prepared for the people of God, and an entrance thereinto many have and do witneſs, and are <hi>ſet down in heavenly Places, with Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> and this Reſt and Glory was before the World was; not a <hi>formed,</hi> but that which <hi>Chriſt</hi> teſtifies of, <hi>he had with the Father before the World was;</hi> and this ſhall abide when all thy imaginations ſhall ceaſe, and thy <hi>formed Reſt</hi> fail thee: O how reſtleſs then ſhalt thou be, when thy hope ſhall periſh! but our hope ſtanding in him, that <hi>is without beginning of dayes or end of life,</hi> we ſhall never be aſhamed; and all <hi>that have this hope purifie themſelves as God is pure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So to thy imagined Reſt, thou art left, where thy trouble and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58809:21"/>
will be increaſed, though thou and thoſe deceived by thee, and their own evil hearts, have rejoyced in iniquity, and if any by diſobedience to or unbelieving in the Light have been overtaken with evil, or run into the pollutions of this World, this you Backſliders have gotten to ſtrengthen you in your envy and back-drawing, though your own appearance manifeſts you are one with them that have forſaken the good Way of God, and the precious Truth, to return to the vanities and cuſtoms of this preſent World, denying his blood that hath calld out of the World, and the Judgments of him that judgeth in Righteouſneſs you ſhall not eſcape; but as one ſhall you all be judged, which have <hi>diſpiſed the Spirit of Grace,</hi> or have turned from it into <hi>wantonneſs;</hi> ſo your portion ſhall be one from firſt to laſt, that have left the good way of God, and profained the Name of that Power and Life in which we that believe have and do know the fulfilling of the promiſe, and are become partakers of the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> and born again thereof, and thereby to inherit <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>immortality,</hi> and an <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Kingdom</hi> which all you are ſhut out of, and have no part in.</p>
               <p>And know to the increaſe of your torment, that have writ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Light, thouſands in faithfulneſs thereto, are <hi>kept out of the pollutions,</hi> yea, and <hi>love of this World,</hi> and witneſs <hi>redemption out of all that which muſt come to an end,</hi> and to us are daily added, and ſhall be added, all that ſhall he ſaved; we have not believed a Lye, but the Truth, and it is ſtronger then all, and ſhall wear out your <hi>Envy,</hi> and ſhall overcome all your <hi>invented Images</hi> and Miſchiefs that you have diviſed againſt the Lord and his Anointed; for the expectations of the Righteous in all generations is come, and who through the regeneration have paſſed, are ſat down on Thrones, and do and ſhall judge the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward you cannot ſee nor pertake of, who have been unfaithful to him that called you, and ſo never came to the Election, but have betrayed it, as faras it lay in you, and have <hi>grieved many little ones;</hi> and better had it been for ſome of you, that <hi>you had never been born,</hi> or that <hi>a Milſtone had been hung about your necks, and you thrown into the bottom of the Sea,</hi> then <hi>a wrought the work of evil againſt the Lord and his Truth,</hi> which he will more and more <hi>raiſe</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58809:22"/>
                  <hi>up and increaſe</hi> againſt and over all the ſtrength of Hell; and they, and they only, are thy Friends R. C. that in plainneſs warns thee of the wrath to come, which ſhall overtake thee, and all that harden their hearts, and ſtop their ears againſt that which ſomtimes pricks them, though they kicks againſt it; and ſome that are ſtout-hearted ſhall confeſs unto, when <hi>their Joy and Hope ſhall come to an end;</hi> but the Lovers and Obeyers of <hi>the true Light</hi> have Peace and Joy in that which is <hi>endleſs</hi> and <hi>everlaſting;</hi> therefore the <hi>evil purpoſes,</hi> and <hi>accuſations,</hi> and <hi>threats of thoſe that diſobey the Goſpel</hi> cannot diſturb nor make us afraid.</p>
               <p>So we would that all men (with us that believe in the Light) might come to the <hi>knowledg of God and be ſaved;</hi> but who hate the Light abide in darkneſs, and brings forth confuſion as R. C. hath done, and there I leave him; only Query of him, as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:58809:22"/>
                  <hi>I.</hi> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the Light and Witneſs (thou ſayeſt) the Quakers declares of the worm that will never dies; then, where is the Reſt thou ſaid'ſt before that God had made or created for his People in the Light in or of the Conſcience? anſwer.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>II.</hi> Do'ſt thou imagine the Worm that never dies, and the Reſt to be both one? anſwer if thou canſt.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>III.</hi> And I query, ſince thou haſt given ſo many names to the Light in or of the Conſcience, for it ſeems thou knoweſt not which; ſaying, It is the Dwelling of God; and ſometimes a formed Light; and ſometimes a Reſt for the People of God; and ſometimes Natures Light; and the Spirit of a man; and the Worm that ſhall never dye: I query, if the ſpirit of a man, and natures light be a Dwelling and Reſt for God and his People that he hath given to Chriſt, as thou haſt ſaid? prove if thou canſt by Scripture.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>IV.</hi> I query of thee, what the Conſcience is, of whoſe light in or of thou haſt brought forth ſo many ſtrange Images? and though thou haſt not brought one Scripture for thy many names of the Light in or of the Conſcience; what is Conſcience? declare if thou canſt.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>V.</hi> I query, if thou canſt bring any Scripture for proving God's Dwelling and his people in the Light of the humane Soul? or that the ſpirit of man is the Reſt? or that the Reſt and the Worm that never dyes be the Light of or in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience as thou affirmeſt? Anſwer if thou canſt.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Query, Was it not the true Chriſt of which <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks, he was ſlain in the great Street ſpiritually called <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Sodom?</hi> and is he ſlain in that Perſon that was viſible at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> or who, or where? Anſwer if thou canſt.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>VII.</hi> I query, <hi>John</hi> ſaith, he that is born of God ſins not, how ſhould he? for the Seed of God abides in him: is that Seed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58809:23"/>
Chriſt in his Perſon? Anſwer, for the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, he ſpeaks not of Seeds many, but the one Seed Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Query, And did this promiſed Seed Chriſt never break the Serpent's head? but in the Perſon which was made manifeſt at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> and if he did, where and how? anſwer.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>IX.</hi> Query, Whether it was the Perſon at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that came down from Heaven and was the Son of man in heaven? that could only aſcend to Heaven, or what? Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>X.</hi> Query, And whether that Talent taken from the unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Servant, and given to another, was the Worm that never dies? or a formative Light? or the ſpirit of the earthly humane Soul? or the Tree of Knowledge of good and evil, as E. A. talks of? or what? Anſwer if thou canſt.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>XI.</hi> Query, Whether doth the Son of God abide with his to the end of the World? is it in Light or in Perſon? Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>XII.</hi> Query, Whether Chriſt, who told his Diſciples he that was with them would be in them, whether he hath ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled his Promiſe? (for he cannot lye) and if in them, is it in Perſon or by Light? Anſwer plainly.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> Query, Whether the Unction or Anointing (which the Apoſtles ſaid ſhould teach them all things) was Chriſt in his Perſon without, or Chriſt in them? anſwer.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>XIV.</hi> Query, Chriſt told<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thoſe that followed him, except they eat his Fleſh and drink his Blood they had no life in him: So I query, whether it was that Perſon they were to eat and drink, or what? if thou canſt, anſwer.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <hi>XV.</hi> Chriſt ſaith, he that eats my Fleſh, and drinks my Blood hath Eternal Life; now I query, if they eat that Perſon? or who they are that have Eternal Life? anſwer if thou canſt.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>XVI.</hi> Chriſt ſaith, he that eats my Fleſh and drinks my Blood dwelleth in me, and I in him; now I query, if this dwelling be in Perſon, or in Light? anſwer plainly.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:58809:23"/>
                  <hi>XVII.</hi> Query, Whether the Accuſer of the Brethren that was to be caſt down from Heaven was the ſpirit of a man? or the light of nature? or the Worm that ſhall never dye? or the Habitation and Dwelling Place for God and his people? ſince in thy writings thou mak'ſt all theſe one; Anſwer plainly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="response">
               <head>
                  <hi>Several Lyes in</hi> R. C<hi>'s Second Page.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. THat we ſay Chriſt is only an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. <note place="margin">Theſe are but a few of thy many falſe Accuſations.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>2<hi>:</hi> That we deſpiſe his Fleſh, and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple his Blood under our feet.</item>
                  <item>3. That we ſet up the creaturely light in Conſcience, for Chriſt and his Light.</item>
                  <item>4. That we deny him to be the Chriſt that in his Perſon was an Offering for Sin.</item>
                  <item>5. That we deny Chriſt in Heaven.</item>
                  <item>6. In thy 16th page, that our Teachers teach entrance into Reſt by Works of obedience to the Light of Nature.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe things thou never heard'ſt nor read'ſt by any of thoſe thou call'ſt our Preachers: So thou publiſheſt to the World, that we hold that which thou think'ſt, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'ſt thy ſelf a falſe Accuſer.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:58809:24"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>THis roſe in my heart for your ſakes, that would know the will of God to do it, and are rather wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to have him work your works in you, then labour in your own imaginations to know and comprehend the incomprehenſible God in your minds, where all Images and idolatrous Worſhips have been framed and brought forth, yea from the ſame ground all wickedneſs and blaſphemies, from the firſt tranſgreſſion to this day, by all that went out from God, and then as <hi>Cain</hi> would offer of their own; and ſo have his generation all along to this day, thoſe born of the Fleſh, warred againſt thoſe born of the Spirit, who worſhipped in the Faith, as we do, confeſſing to know nothing of God and his everlaſting Truth, but as we are taught and led of this Spirit, and in this know both Father and Son, and receive power thereby to become the Sons and Daughters of God; and cannot but declare of his Glory and Good will who hath ſent us, that according to the meaſure received of him, we may Glorifie him; of whoſe Grace we have received Grace for Grace; and know his continued Good will, even to all and every one that believes in his Light and Word of which the Scriptures teſtifie, both by Prophets and Apoſtles, as it is written, <hi>Amos</hi> 4. 13. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 12. and of another Light and Word did we never Write or Declare; then of Jeſus the Firſt and the Laſt, which they that have erred from, are offering deſpite to us, as R. C.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58809:24"/>
in his Practice and Writing doth; who having walked ſome Years amongſt us, as if he had been one of us, yet not bowing to, nor believing in the true Light, where Power is received, grew in Envy againſt thoſe that were in it, by which he and ſuch like have been given up to a Reprobate Minde, to change the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible God into the likeneſs of Corruptible Things, as R. C. hath in his firſt and laſt; as may be ſeen and read in his vain Imaginations of God and Chriſt; utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Lyes and Blaſphemies againſt God and his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, ſome of which I have in my foregoing lines recited, that all may ſee he is contrary to Scriptures and Truth, and to us, that no more any may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by him.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Rebecca Traverſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 6. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>for</hi> were, <hi>read</hi> was. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>for</hi> ſaith thou, <hi>read</hi> ſay'ſt thou. <hi>Pag.</hi> 13. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>for</hi> thou comeſt to be, <hi>read</hi> thou comeſt to ſee. <hi>P.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>for</hi> and they his, <hi>read</hi> and theirs. <hi>P.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>blot out</hi> too, and. <hi>P.</hi> 23. <hi>l.</hi> 35. <hi>for</hi> thy ſeeming, <hi>read</hi> ſeem.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
